<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0 ../schemas/akomantoso30.xsd " xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd" xmlns:gpo="http://www.loc.gov/presentation/v1">
  <doc contains="originalVersion" name="784e6dfa-2d89-4b05-a132-d17973cc035a">
    <meta>
      <identification source="Minnesota Administrative Rules">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250"/>
          <FRBRuri value="https://www.revisor.mn.gov/rules/agency/127"/>
          <FRBRalias name="" value=""/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-12-15T12:15:35Z" name="Publication Date"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="" as="Minnesota State Legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="US-MN"/>
          <FRBRsubtype value="ADMINISTRATIVE_COMPILATION"/>
          <FRBRnumber value=""/>
          <FRBRname value="Minnesota"/>
          <FRBRprescriptive value="true"/>
          <FRBRauthoritative value="true"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250"/>
          <FRBRuri value="https://www.revisor.mn.gov/rules/agency/127"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-12-15T12:15:35Z" name="Last Updated Date"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="" as="Minnesota State Legislature"/>
          <FRBRversionNumber value="https://github.com/R2ai/data-dcl/tree/master/US/US-MN/sdc-minnesota-rules.xml"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="English"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250"/>
          <FRBRuri value="https://www.revisor.mn.gov/rules/agency/127"/>
          <FRBRalias name="" value=""/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-12-15T12:15:35Z" name="Processing Date"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="" as="DCL"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
    </meta>
    <mainBody GUID="784e6dfa-2d89-4b05-a132-d17973cc035a">
      <hcontainer GUID="7569819a-daf9-482e-9a7b-8dc083617cf9" name="2" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250">
        <level>
          <content>
            <p><shortTitle><inline name="num">Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250</inline></shortTitle></p>
          </content>
        </level>
        <hcontainer GUID="57550bac-b939-4277-aeed-235754c79393" name="3" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle><inline name="num">3250</inline> BOARD OF DIETETICS AND NUTRITION PRACTICE LICENSURE AND PRACTICE</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="a1903831-489b-457c-9091-058b63951d8d" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0010">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0010</inline> <b>REQUIREMENTS FOR LICENSURE AS A DIETITIAN.</b></shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
            <hcontainer GUID="27ad16b6-f93b-4afe-a277-28eb83edb17e" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0010/SUBPART 1.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subpart <inline name="num">1</inline>. <b>Generally.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>To be eligible for licensure as a dietitian, an applicant must submit a fully completed application on a form provided by the board, along with the applicable fee as provided in part 3250.0050, and meet one of the sets of requirements described in subparts 2 to 4.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="3a65cf0d-4b4f-419f-a44d-472dde19db16" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0010/SUBPART 2.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">2</inline>. <b>Education and experience.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>The applicant must provide the board with:</p>
                  <p>A. an official transcript showing that the applicant has received a baccalaureate or postgraduate degree with a major in dietetics, human nutrition, nutrition education, food and nutrition, or food services management from a United States regionally accredited college or university;</p>
                  <p>B. documented evidence of having completed a supervised preprofessional practice experience component in nutrition practice of at least 900 hours under the supervision of a registered dietitian, a state licensed nutrition professional, or an individual with a doctoral degree conferred by a United States regionally accredited college or university who has completed a major course of study in human nutrition, nutrition education, food and nutrition, dietetics, or food system management. Supervised practice experience must be completed in the United States or its territories. Supervisors who obtain their doctoral degrees outside the United States and its territories must have their degrees approved by the board as equivalent to the doctoral degree conferred by a United States regionally accredited college or university; and</p>
                  <p>C. documented evidence of successful completion of the registration examination for dietitians administered by the Commission on Dietetic Registration within five years immediately preceding application for licensure.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="41e1d15c-a7c5-439b-baaa-6f8a8f0fb8fb" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0010/SUBPART 3.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">3</inline>. <b>National registration.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>The applicant must provide a notarized copy of the applicant's current registration card from the Commission on Dietetic Registration demonstrating registration as a dietitian.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="8e2a2b89-4676-4786-a78f-bcc8b019326b" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0010/SUBPART 4.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">4</inline>. <b>Applicants holding foreign degrees.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>An applicant with a foreign degree must provide:</p>
                  <p>A. documented evidence that an evaluating agency preapproved by the board has evaluated the applicant's transcript from a foreign college or university and has deemed the transcript to be equivalent to the transcript required under subpart 2, item A. The documented evidence must be received directly from the evaluating agency by the board;</p>
                  <p>B. documented evidence of having completed within the last five years a supervised preprofessional experience component in nutrition practice of at least 900 hours under the supervision of a registered dietitian, a state licensed nutrition professional, or an individual with a doctoral degree conferred by a United States regionally accredited college or university who has completed a major course of study in human nutrition, nutrition education, food and nutrition, dietetics, or food system management. Supervised practice experience must be completed in the United States or its territories. Supervisors who obtain their doctoral degrees outside the United States and its territories must have their degrees approved by the board as equivalent to the doctoral degree conferred by a United States regionally accredited college or university; and</p>
                  <p>C. documented evidence of successful completion of the registration examination administered by the Commission on Dietetic Registration within five years immediately preceding application for licensure.</p>
                  <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                  <p>MS s 148.623; 214.06</p>
                  <p><b>History:</b></p>
                  <p>20 SR 1288</p>
                  <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                  <p>November 13, 2019</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="cc96c0c9-5753-44b2-b721-41bf404df256" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0020">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0020</inline> <b>NUTRITIONIST REQUIREMENTS.</b></shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
            <hcontainer GUID="d9ee3b7f-2808-4577-819f-8a196f7003dd" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0020/SUBPART 1.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subpart <inline name="num">1</inline>. <b>Generally.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>To be eligible for licensure as a nutritionist, an applicant must submit a fully completed application on a form provided by the board, along with the applicable fee as provided in part 3250.0050, and meet one of the sets of requirements described in subparts 2 to 5.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="d438bb3a-c63b-49e9-98f0-78f27b127f8e" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0020/SUBPART 2.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">2</inline>. <b>Education and experience.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>The applicant must provide the board with:</p>
                  <p>A. an official transcript showing that the applicant has received a postgraduate degree with a major in human nutrition, public health nutrition, clinical nutrition, nutrition education, community nutrition, or food and nutrition from a United States regionally accredited college or university; and</p>
                  <p>B. documented evidence of having completed a supervised preprofessional practice experience component in nutrition practice of at least 900 hours under the supervision of a registered dietitian, a state licensed nutrition professional, or an individual with a doctoral degree conferred by a United States regionally accredited college or university who has completed a major course of study in human nutrition, nutrition education, food and nutrition, dietetics, or food system management. Supervised practice experience must be completed in the United States or its territories. Supervisors who obtain their doctoral degrees outside the United States and its territories must have their degrees approved by the board as equivalent to the doctoral degree conferred by a United States regionally accredited college or university.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="01368290-b987-415a-9870-8dc0554d5975" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0020/SUBPART 3.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">3</inline>. <b>National registration.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>The applicant must provide a notarized copy of a current certificate showing the applicant's diplomate status with the American Board of Nutrition.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="d62ac42e-8595-4beb-94d8-e865159b2c39" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0020/SUBPART 4.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">4</inline>. <b>Applicants petitioning for independent review.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>The applicant petitioning for independent review must provide the board with:</p>
                  <p>A. an official transcript showing the applicant's completion of a master's or doctoral degree with a major course of study that includes an emphasis in human nutrition, as described in Minnesota Statutes, section 148.624, subdivision 3, paragraph (a); and</p>
                  <p>B. documented evidence of having completed a supervised preprofessional practice experience component in nutrition practice of at least 900 hours under the supervision of a registered dietitian, a state licensed nutrition professional, or an individual with a doctoral degree conferred by a United States regionally accredited college or university who has completed a major course of study in human nutrition, nutrition education, food and nutrition, dietetics, or food system management. Supervised practice experience must be completed in the United States or its territories. Supervisors who obtain their doctoral degrees outside the United States and its territories must have their degrees approved by the board as equivalent to the doctoral degree conferred by a United States regionally accredited college or university.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="f495a80c-2128-40dd-b253-ceba1c720d89" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0020/SUBPART 5.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">5</inline>. <b>Applicants holding foreign degrees.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>The applicant holding a foreign degree must provide the board with:</p>
                  <p>A. documented evidence that an evaluating agency, preapproved by the board, has evaluated the applicant's transcript from a foreign college or university and has deemed that transcript to be equivalent to the transcript required under subpart 2, item A. The documented evidence must be received directly from the evaluating agency by the board; and</p>
                  <p>B. documented evidence of having completed within the last five years a supervised preprofessional experience component in nutrition practice of at least 900 hours under the supervision of a registered dietitian, a state licensed nutrition professional, or an individual with a doctoral degree conferred by a United States regionally accredited college or university who has completed a major course of study in human nutrition, nutrition education, food and nutrition, dietetics, and food system management. Supervised practice experience must be completed in the United States or its territories. Supervisors who obtain their doctoral degrees outside the United States and its territories must have their degrees approved by the board as equivalent to the doctoral degree conferred by a United States regionally accredited college or university.</p>
                  <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                  <p>MS s 148.623; 214.06</p>
                  <p><b>History:</b></p>
                  <p>20 SR 1288</p>
                  <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                  <p>October 19, 2000</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="d7ff9ebf-27f7-40d2-bce0-18cea05bd770" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0030">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0030</inline> <b>TRANSITION PERIOD REQUIREMENTS.</b></shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
            <hcontainer GUID="360bc9f9-ba16-4d45-bab5-09f81279425d" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0030/SUBPART 1.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subpart <inline name="num">1</inline>. <b>Dietitian requirements.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>To be eligible for licensure as a dietitian for one year from December 11, 1995, in lieu of the requirements in part 3250.0010, an applicant must submit to the board a fully completed application on a form provided by the board, along with the applicable fee as provided in part 3250.0050, and provide:</p>
                  <p>A. a notarized copy of the applicant's current registration card from the Commission on Dietetic Registration demonstrating registration as a dietitian or an official transcript from a United States regionally accredited college or university showing the applicant received a bachelor's degree in dietetics, human nutrition, nutrition education, food and nutrition, or food service management; and</p>
                  <p>B. a letter from an employer or colleague attesting to the applicant's competent practice of dietetics for the equivalent of one year in the last five years.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="a6b95c89-681c-4be2-8d5a-2996ef65e969" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0030/SUBPART 2.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">2</inline>. <b>Nutritionist requirements.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>To be eligible for licensure as a nutritionist for one year from December 11, 1995, in lieu of the requirements in part 3250.0020, an applicant must submit a fully completed application, on a form provided by the board, along with the applicable fee as provided under part 3250.0050, and provide the board with evidence of meeting one of the sets of requirements described in item A, B, or C:</p>
                  <p>A. an official transcript from an accredited or approved college or university showing that the applicant has received a master's or doctoral degree with a major in human nutrition, public health nutrition, clinical nutrition, nutrition education, community nutrition, or food and nutrition and a letter from an employer or colleague attesting to the applicant's competent practice of nutrition or dietetics for the equivalent of one year in the last five years;</p>
                  <p>B. a notarized copy of current certification as a clinical nutritionist from the International and American Association of Clinical Nutritionists and a letter attesting to the applicant's competent practice of clinical nutrition, from a medical doctor with whom the applicant is working; or</p>
                  <p>C. a notarized copy of the applicant's current certification as a nutrition specialist from the Board of Nutrition Specialists.</p>
                  <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                  <p>MS s 148.623; 214.06</p>
                  <p><b>History:</b></p>
                  <p>20 SR 1288</p>
                  <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                  <p>October 19, 2000</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="c9f2ef3c-d703-4c77-84f1-ea0c245e70a6" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0040">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0040</inline> <b>INITIAL LICENSING.</b></shortTitle></p>
                <p>The board shall review and grant licenses on a quarterly basis, during the second full week of the months of November, February, May, and August, provided the date is no later than the 15th day of the month.</p>
                <p>An application must be received before the first day of the month in which the application will be reviewed by the board.</p>
                <p>Licenses granted in November 1995 shall be effective December 1, 1995, through November 30, 1996. Thereafter, a license shall be effective on the date it is approved by the board through the following month of November.</p>
                <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                <p>MS s 148.623; 214.06</p>
                <p><b>History:</b></p>
                <p>20 SR 1288</p>
                <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                <p>October 19, 2000</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="ff2b47e3-5f37-4e81-ac94-e06931a59d4b" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0045">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0045</inline> <b>TERMS AND RENEWAL OF LICENSE.</b></shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
            <hcontainer GUID="96e611a4-9b22-4c7c-a01e-8ee6b124f552" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0045/SUBPART 1.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subpart <inline name="num">1</inline>. <b>Renewal of license.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>To renew a license, a licensee shall submit an application for renewal to the board, postmarked no later than November 30 of each year.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="3e31d597-0317-4751-9980-3fda39e4cd7c" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0045/SUBPART 2.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">2</inline>. <b>Voluntary termination.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>A licensee may indicate on the application for renewal that the licensee wishes to voluntarily terminate the license.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="c7a30cea-5245-4d31-a975-785bdf085638" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0045/SUBPART 3.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">3</inline>. <b>Failure to submit renewal application.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>A licensee who has not renewed the license by November 30 must be notified by letter by December 30. The letter must be sent to the last known address of the licensee in the file of the board and must state that the renewal is overdue and that failure to pay the current fee and current late fee by January 30 will result in termination of the license. A second notice must be sent by first class mail to each licensee who has not paid the renewal fee and late fee at least seven days before the first board meeting to occur after January 30. This notice must state that board action will be taken to terminate the license of a person who has not responded to the first notice.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="bfea41d6-2de7-484d-9822-1c223393dd46" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0045/SUBPART 4.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">4</inline>. <b>Termination due to nonrenewal of license.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>The board shall terminate the license of a licensee whose license renewal has not been received by January 30 and to whom notification has been sent as provided in subpart 3. Failure of a licensee to receive notification because of the licensee's failure to provide the board with a current mailing address is not grounds for later challenge by the licensee of the termination. The former licensee must be notified by first class mail within seven days of the board action. The terminated status placed on a license may be removed by following the criteria of part 3250.0150 for reinstatement.</p>
                  <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                  <p>MS s 148.623; 148.624; 214.06</p>
                  <p><b>History:</b></p>
                  <p>25 SR 779</p>
                  <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                  <p>October 19, 2000</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="c3a501e0-0e00-4d82-8d99-915cf9933711" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0050">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0050</inline> <b>FEE SCHEDULE.</b></shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
            <hcontainer GUID="9234c606-9491-4d2e-8709-676a37ffa2cf" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0050/SUBPART 1.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subpart <inline name="num">1</inline>. <b>Application fees.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>Application fees must be submitted along with an application to the board office. The fees are as follows:</p>
                  <p>A. nutritionist or dietitian by petition, $200;</p>
                  <p>B. nutritionist, $175;</p>
                  <p>C. dietitian without registration by the Commission on Dietetic Registration, $175; and</p>
                  <p>D. dietitian with registration by the Commission on Dietetic Registration, $100.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="94bac4bd-6750-4ec2-bb5c-96d45369a762" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0050/SUBPART 2.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">2</inline>. <b>Licensing fee.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>An initial licensing fee must be submitted along with the application for licensure to the board office. The initial licensing fee is $150.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="d453bb47-d14d-4b5e-96b3-8a206cb4455e" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0050/SUBPART 3.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">3</inline>. <b>License renewal fee.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>Annual renewal fees are due by November 30 of each year. The annual renewal fee is $75.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="b67a8fe4-edb7-406b-9833-9316ae5c3ff5" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0050/SUBPART 4.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">4</inline>. <b>Late renewal penalty.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>Renewal requests postmarked after November 30 shall be assessed a late penalty fee equal to 50 percent of the current annual renewal fee.</p>
                  <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                  <p>MS s 148.623; 148.624; 214.06</p>
                  <p><b>History:</b></p>
                  <p>20 SR 1288; 22 SR 596; 23 SR 1151; 25 SR 779</p>
                  <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                  <p>October 19, 2000</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="96843095-1ac2-45aa-83a7-4ce2bffbf83c" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0100">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0100</inline> <b>PURPOSE.</b></shortTitle></p>
                <p>The primary purpose of continuing education is to ensure the public of an optimum quality of dietetic and nutrition care by requiring dietitians and nutritionists to take part in educational programs designed to advance their professional skills and knowledge.</p>
                <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                <p>MS s 148.623; 214.06; 214.12</p>
                <p><b>History:</b></p>
                <p>22 SR 595</p>
                <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                <p>October 19, 2000</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="9fa04f5a-e93b-4a9c-9348-90e312e1f708" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0110">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0110</inline> <b>DEFINITIONS.</b></shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
            <hcontainer GUID="9ca6da4d-bdce-405b-a0a2-bb33d05c8eb0" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0110/SUBPART 1.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subpart <inline name="num">1</inline>. <b>Scope.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>For the purposes of parts 3250.0110 to 3250.0150, the terms in this part have the meanings given them.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="6951aeea-71fd-4349-aeaa-cfb00466a8a9" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0110/SUBPART 2.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">2</inline>. <b>Program.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>"Program" means an educational activity related to the practice of dietetics and nutrition that offers a specified number of continuing education units. Programs shall be approved by the board or a board-recognized reviewer.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="ea42fa5a-4ffa-420b-96bf-0926b75ef05a" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0110/SUBPART 3.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">3</inline>. <b>Unit.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>"Unit" means the equivalent of one clock hour of credit for participation in a program. Units per program shall be determined by the board or board-recognized reviewer. Refreshment breaks and lunches do not count for unit credit.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="12b97692-5321-4c55-b604-71abc3408afe" name="5" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0110/SUBPART 4.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>Subp. <inline name="num">4</inline>. <b>Board-recognized reviewer.</b></shortTitle></p>
                  <p>"Board-recognized reviewer" means an organization, approved by the board, that has and maintains current knowledge of dietetics and nutrition necessary to determine whether the program content meets the criteria outlined in part 3250.0130.</p>
                  <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                  <p>MS s 148.623; 214.06; 214.12</p>
                  <p><b>History:</b></p>
                  <p>22 SR 595</p>
                  <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                  <p>October 19, 2000</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="fedc71d3-3475-4173-86d7-89c04bb9b2ce" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0120">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0120</inline> <b>REQUIRED CONTINUING EDUCATION.</b></shortTitle></p>
                <p>Each person licensed to practice dietetics and nutrition in this state shall, as a prerequisite for the continued renewal of the person's license, obtain a minimum of 45 continuing education units every three years by participating in board-approved continuing education programs.</p>
                <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                <p>MS s 148.623; 214.06; 214.12</p>
                <p><b>History:</b></p>
                <p>22 SR 595</p>
                <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                <p>October 19, 2000</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="e6093775-63b1-45bb-a23d-9ff81930bb9d" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0125">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0125</inline> <b>QUALIFYING UNITS.</b></shortTitle></p>
                <p>In order to meet the requirements of part 3250.0120, programs and the assigned number of units for the program must be approved by the board. The board shall approve programs that meet the criteria specified in part 3250.0130. Alternatively, the board shall accept programs approved by board-recognized reviewers. Board approval of programs may be sought by the licensed individual or the sponsor of a program. Board approval of programs may be sought either in advance of or after participation in the program. Units may be obtained through a variety of formats, including, but not limited to, classes, conferences, correspondence study courses, lectures, seminars, study groups, exhibits, poster presentations, and publications.</p>
                <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                <p>MS s 148.623; 214.06; 214.12</p>
                <p><b>History:</b></p>
                <p>22 SR 595</p>
                <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                <p>October 19, 2000</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="79fea575-bdbb-4818-89ce-824cc068f5bf" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0130">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0130</inline> <b>CONTINUING EDUCATION APPROVAL CRITERIA.</b></shortTitle></p>
                <p>The board and board-recognized reviewers shall use the following criteria to determine whether to approve continuing education programs and to determine how many units to assign to each program:</p>
                <p>A. the extent to which the material to be presented is likely to enhance knowledge and skill in the practice of dietetics and nutrition, as defined in Minnesota Statutes, section 148.621;</p>
                <p>B. the extent to which instructors or speakers presenting the program are qualified in the field of instruction, either by practical or academic experience or both;</p>
                <p>C. the program sponsor has furnished or agrees to furnish evidence of program participation by Minnesota licensees; and</p>
                <p>D. the complexity of material and participation time involved.</p>
                <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                <p>MS s 148.623; 214.06; 214.12</p>
                <p><b>History:</b></p>
                <p>22 SR 595</p>
                <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                <p>October 19, 2000</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="be705a89-f461-4c13-b99a-1bcfcb7752ac" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0135">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0135</inline> <b>RECORD OF APPROVED PROGRAMS.</b></shortTitle></p>
                <p>The board shall maintain a record of approved programs and recognized reviewers of continuing education.</p>
                <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                <p>MS s 148.623; 214.06; 214.12</p>
                <p><b>History:</b></p>
                <p>22 SR 595</p>
                <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                <p>October 19, 2000</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="a2ea69ae-a38a-4326-9e81-bf133d5afcb6" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0140">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0140</inline> <b>SCHEDULE OF REQUIRED CONTINUING EDUCATION UNITS.</b></shortTitle></p>
                <p>A. Continuing education cycles shall run every three years, beginning December 1, 1997.</p>
                <p>B. Each dietitian or nutritionist licensed on or before December 1, 1997, shall obtain 45 continuing education units by November 30, 2000, in order to annually renew a license for the period December 1, 2000, through November 30, 2003. Thereafter, each dietitian or nutritionist shall obtain 45 units every three years as a condition of annual license renewal.</p>
                <p>C. Each dietitian or nutritionist licensed after December 1, 1997, shall be responsible for obtaining a proportion of the requisite continuing education units for the continuing education cycle in which that person enters as follows:</p>
                <p>(1) if licensed during the first year of the cycle, for example, between December 1, 1997, and November 30, 1998, the individual shall obtain 30 units by the end of the cycle;</p>
                <p>(2) if licensed during the second year of the cycle, for example, between December 1, 1998, and November 30, 1999, the individual shall obtain 15 units by the end of the cycle; and</p>
                <p>(3) if licensed during the third year of the cycle, for example, between December 1, 1999, and November 30, 2000, the individual is exempt from obtaining any units by the end of the cycle.</p>
                <p>Thereafter, the individual shall obtain 45 units during each three-year cycle.</p>
                <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                <p>MS s 148.623; 214.06; 214.12</p>
                <p><b>History:</b></p>
                <p>22 SR 595</p>
                <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                <p>October 19, 2000</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="418915ed-fa63-499d-8f57-7df6d2e11828" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0145">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0145</inline> <b>REPORTING CONTINUING EDUCATION.</b></shortTitle></p>
                <p>A. Every three years beginning November 30, 2000, each individual licensed by the board shall report to the board approved continuing education units obtained during the preceding three years. The number of reported units shall be at least 45 or the appropriate portion of units as specified in part 3250.0140. In addition to reporting continuing education units on the form provided by the board, each licensee shall be prepared to provide to the board, upon request, evidence of completion of all reported units.</p>
                <p>B. Failure to comply with item A shall result in the licensee's license not being renewed.</p>
                <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                <p>MS s 148.623; 214.06; 214.12</p>
                <p><b>History:</b></p>
                <p>22 SR 595</p>
                <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                <p>October 19, 2000</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="240f7ce4-440f-41c6-93ea-a04ff646ba56" name="4" class="/US/US-MN/MINNESOTA_ADMINISTRATIVE_RULES/Dietetics and Nutrition Practice Board 3250/3250/3250.0150">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>3250.<inline name="num">0150</inline> <b>REINSTATEMENT.</b></shortTitle></p>
                <p>A licensee who voluntarily terminated the license or whose license was terminated by board action shall, in order to have the licensee's license reinstated:</p>
                <p>A. submit to the board a completed reinstatement application on a form provided by the board;</p>
                <p>B. submit evidence to the board of having obtained the required continuing education units for the continuing education cycle in effect at the time that the licensee's license was terminated;</p>
                <p>C. submit evidence to the board of having met the continuing education requirements that would have applied to the licensee during the period of time between the termination of the license and the application for reinstatement had the licensee held a license during that time; and</p>
                <p>D. submit to the board the appropriate reinstatement fee which shall be the current annual renewal and late penalty fees plus an administrative charge of $25.</p>
                <p><b>Statutory Authority:</b></p>
                <p>MS s 148.623; 214.06; 214.12</p>
                <p><b>History:</b></p>
                <p>22 SR 595; 25 SR 779</p>
                <p><b>Published Electronically:</b></p>
                <p>October 19, 2000</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
      </hcontainer>
    </mainBody>
  </doc>
</akomaNtoso>

