<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0 ../schemas/akomantoso30.xsd " xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-6.xsd" xmlns:gpo="http://www.loc.gov/presentation/v1">
  <doc contains="originalVersion" name="d7038c3b-00b1-4184-8b99-0725dd65bb75">
    <meta>
      <identification source="Wyoming Statutes">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25"/>
          <FRBRuri value="https://wyoleg.gov/statutes/compress/title25.pdf"/>
          <FRBRalias name="" value=""/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-10-21T10:21:22Z" name="Publication Date"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="" as="Wyoming State Legislature"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="US-WY"/>
          <FRBRsubtype value="Statute"/>
          <FRBRnumber value=""/>
          <FRBRname value="Wyoming"/>
          <FRBRprescriptive value="true"/>
          <FRBRauthoritative value="true"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25"/>
          <FRBRuri value="https://wyoleg.gov/statutes/compress/title25.pdf"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-10-21T14:21:22Z" name="Last Updated Date"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="" as="Wyoming State Legislature"/>
          <FRBRversionNumber value="https://github.com/R2ai/data-dcl/tree/master/US/US-WY/brd-wyoming-statutes.xml"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="English"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25"/>
          <FRBRuri value="https://wyoleg.gov/statutes/compress/title25.pdf"/>
          <FRBRalias name="" value=""/>
          <FRBRdate date="2020-10-21T14:21:22Z" name="Processing Date"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="" as="DCL"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
    </meta>
    <mainBody GUID="d7038c3b-00b1-4184-8b99-0725dd65bb75">
      <hcontainer GUID="a16f68cf-92c2-42ba-a1ce-9e48fa1067ba" name="2" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25">
        <level>
          <content>
            <p><shortTitle>TITLE 25 INSTITUTIONS OF THE STATE</shortTitle></p>
          </content>
        </level>
        <hcontainer GUID="1a4fded3-e4a5-4ed0-948a-87cb216b99e1" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 1 GENERAL PROVISIONS</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="7746367d-6c3d-41a6-8f19-f9c6122a12f3" name="4" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1/ARTICLE 1">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>ARTICLE 1 DEPARTMENT OF CORRECTIONS</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
            <hcontainer GUID="96337c3f-3439-4ce9-87bc-bd9a480036d1" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1/ARTICLE 1/25-1-101.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-1-101. Repealed by Laws 1992, ch. 25, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="a1575b01-c2fe-4c15-a744-209664ec3ff3" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1/ARTICLE 1/25-1-102.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-1-102. Repealed by Laws 1992, ch. 25, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="81917729-28ed-42c9-9953-201c96636681" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1/ARTICLE 1/25-1-103.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-1-103. Repealed by Laws 1992, ch. 25, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="9c9b966c-cd6d-4fcc-9f65-0fdb111cf450" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1/ARTICLE 1/25-1-104.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-1-104. Creation of department of corrections; duties; inspections of state institutions; regulation of prisoner produced goods.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) The department of corrections is created. The department consists of the director who is the chief administrative officer and such divisions as the director may create.</p>
                  <p>(b) The department of corrections has general supervision, control and custody of all penal institutions, and responsibility for the maintenance and repair of all buildings and grounds utilized by the institutions. Specifically the department has general supervision and control of, and shall provide for the care and maintenance of all inmates in the following state institutions:</p>
                  <p>(i) Wyoming state penitentiary;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Wyoming honor farms and camps;</p>
                  <p>(iii) Wyoming women's center;</p>
                  <p>(iv) Wyoming medium correctional institution;</p>
                  <p>(v) Adult community correctional facilities defined by W.S. 7-18-102(a)(i).</p>
                  <p>(c) The department of corrections has general supervisory authority over state parolees and, subject to the order of the sentencing court, over probationers for whom the sentencing court requests supervision under W.S. 7-13-410(b).</p>
                  <p>(d) The director shall:</p>
                  <p>(i) Personally inspect all state institutions under the department's supervision and control at least once every year;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Direct the general management of all state penal institutions enumerated in W.S. 25-1-104(b) and be responsible for the proper disbursement of all funds appropriated for their maintenance;</p>
                  <p>(iii) Direct the general management of the state probation and parole program; and</p>
                  <p>(iv) Appoint, prescribe the duties of, and remove at will the following officers:</p>
                  <p>(A) Wardens of the Wyoming state penitentiary, medium correctional institution, women's center and Wyoming honor farms and camps;</p>
                  <p>(B) Repealed by Laws 2005, ch. 93, \xA7 2.</p>
                  <p>(C) Repealed By Laws 2005, ch. 93, \xA7 2.</p>
                  <p>(D) The state probation and parole officer.</p>
                  <p>(e) The officers provided for under W.S. 25-1-104(d)(iv)(A) and (D) shall:</p>
                  <p>(i) Serve as administrator of and manage the institutions to which they are appointed subject to the supervision of the director;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Employ personnel necessary and approved by the director and the Wyoming legislature;</p>
                  <p>(iii) Report to the director as required.</p>
                  <p>(f) The director may appoint and may remove at will a deputy director and division administrators.</p>
                  <p>(g) The department shall establish rules and regulations regarding the provision of services and the production of goods by prisoners at all state corrections institutions including but not limited to labor requirements, wage rates, use of goods within the institution of origin, sales price and method of distribution to other institutions or the general public. In promulgating rules relating to correctional industries programs authorized by W.S. 25-13-101 through 25-13-107, the department shall adhere to the requirements of the private sector prison industry enhancement certification program of the federal bureau of justice assistance. Rules and regulations promulgated under this subsection shall place limitations on competition with the private sector and will ensure that no contract entered into under W.S. 25-13-101 through 25-13-107 will result in the displacement of employed workers in the state in excess of limitations established by the correctional industries advisory board created by W.S. 25-13-102.</p>
                  <p>(h) The department of corrections has general supervision and control of, and shall provide for the care and maintenance of all inmates who have been placed in institutions of other jurisdictions or private entities pursuant to contracts or agreements under W.S. 25-1-105(e).</p>
                  <p>(j) The director may order returned to the custody of the department any person under the department's jurisdiction. The written order of the director shall be sufficient warrant for any peace officer to return to actual custody any escaped state prisoner or any state prisoner released prior to his scheduled release date or who is about to be released by another jurisdiction prior to his scheduled release date in Wyoming. It is the duty of all peace officers to execute the order of the director issued under this subsection in like manner as ordinary criminal process. A person taken into custody under the order of the director is not subject to release on bail. Consistent with W.S. 7-3-201 through 7-3-227, the director may apply to the governor to seek the extradition of an inmate apprehended in another state pursuant to an order of the director issued under this subsection.</p>
                  <p>(k) The department of corrections shall issue certificates of restoration of voting rights pursuant to W.S. 7-13-105(b) and (c).</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="ebd905ca-d22d-431c-b53e-2b302c8703b1" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1/ARTICLE 1/25-1-105.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-1-105. Powers of department; care of persons committed outside of state.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) The department of corrections shall adopt rules and regulations necessary to carry out its functions. The promulgation of substantive rules by the department, the conduct of its hearings and its final decisions are specifically exempt from all provisions of the Wyoming Administrative Procedure Act including the provisions for judicial review under W.S. 16-3-114 and 16-3-115. The department's rules shall be filed in the office of the secretary of state.</p>
                  <p>(b) The department may enter into contracts with the federal government or other states for the care of persons committed outside of Wyoming.</p>
                  <p>(c) Subject to subsection (d) of this section, the department may, to obtain demonstrable cost savings or better quality of services, contract with private service providers or with other agencies for any of the following services to be provided for inmates of any state adult penal institution:</p>
                  <p>(i) Education, training and jobs programs;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Recreational and religious activities;</p>
                  <p>(iii) Development and implementation assistance for classification, management information systems or other information systems or services;</p>
                  <p>(iv) Medical services;</p>
                  <p>(v) Food services, commissary, transportation, sanitation or other ancillary services; and</p>
                  <p>(vi) Counseling, special treatment programs or other programs for special needs.</p>
                  <p>(d) The department shall by rule and regulation impose upon services contracted pursuant to paragraph (c)(i) of this section limitations on competition with the private sector and ensure contracted services do not significantly displace employed workers within the community.</p>
                  <p>(e) The department of corrections may enter into contracts and agreements with any county for the confinement and maintenance in county jails of persons sentenced to the custody of the department of corrections to serve a term of imprisonment in a state penal institution. The department may enter into contracts and agreements with other states, including those which are not party to the Western Interstate Corrections Compact, with the federal government, with other governmental entities and with private owners and operators of correctional facilities in other states, for the confinement and maintenance of persons sentenced to the custody of the department to serve a term of imprisonment in a state penal institution. The department shall establish rules and regulations regarding the minimum standards for such facilities and standards for the care and treatment of department of correction's inmates incarcerated therein.</p>
                  <p>(f) Pursuant to this section and W.S. 9-2-130, the department of corrections shall collaborate with the department of health to reduce recidivism rates for persons with behavioral health needs and substance use disorders who are involved in the criminal justice system and improve mental health and substance use disorder programming by:</p>
                  <p>(i) Improving the quality and accuracy of substance use assessments administered to persons with criminal justice involvement by creating a quality improvement unit in the department of corrections that will regularly monitor the administration and use of assessment tools. The department of corrections shall report to the joint labor, health and social services interim committee on the status of the unit, including progress on the creation of the unit, results of unit efforts, unit expenditures and remaining funds from appropriations made for the unit. The department of corrections shall provide this report to the joint labor, health and social services interim committee by September 1 of each year through 2023;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Creating a behavioral health services enhancement program for community providers to improve outcomes for persons involved in the criminal justice system through a separate contract, or in a separate provision in an existing contract, administered by the department of health;</p>
                  <p>(iii) Adopting standardized, evidence based treatment practices and guidelines for treating and providing programming to persons involved in the criminal justice system with behavioral health and substance use needs;</p>
                  <p>(iv) Increasing communication between the department of health, the department of corrections and contracted behavioral health providers working with persons involved in the criminal justice system;</p>
                  <p>(v) Promoting and requiring to the maximum extent practical and permissible under applicable laws and regulations the portability and universal recognition of mental health and substance use disorder assessment tools and other assessment tools that may be applicable to mental health and substance use disorder treatment; and</p>
                  <p>(vi) Creating a competitive and outcomes based funding stream for behavioral health providers to:</p>
                  <p>(A) Expand existing services for criminal justice involved populations;</p>
                  <p>(B) Improve the quality and availability of services and programs;</p>
                  <p>(C) Train and develop the skills of providers and stakeholders working with persons who have behavior health needs and substance use disorders and who are involved in the criminal justice system.</p>
                  <p>(g) This section shall not be interpreted to require the creation or maintenance of any duplicate functions, services or programs in the department of corrections and the department of health, but shall be interpreted with W.S. 9-2-130 to require coordination and collaboration between the agencies to assure the creation and maintenance of independent or coordinated functions, services and programs to meet the goals of this section and W.S. 9-2-130.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="276f66c4-5f4c-49c0-b14b-0e6496fc1687" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1/ARTICLE 1/25-1-106.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-1-106. Repealed by Laws 1992, ch. 25, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="54e760d0-0393-4f0b-a5f3-cfccd49cba37" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1/ARTICLE 1/25-1-107.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-1-107. Repealed by Laws 1987, ch. 127, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="c55efd5d-846f-4c21-b719-099f68e54e9d" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1/ARTICLE 1/25-1-108.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-1-108. Repealed by Laws 1987, ch. 127, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="2151b128-0a90-4393-9622-4a81152bf2c7" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1/ARTICLE 1/25-1-109.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-1-109. Repealed by Laws 1987, ch. 127, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="282b8c1d-adb9-473a-951b-9029ebf92d77" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1/ARTICLE 1/25-1-110.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-1-110. Repealed by Laws 1987, ch. 127, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="e1ff8877-b4dd-4bd2-9ce7-09ee53d2e2b8" name="4" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1/ARTICLE 2">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>ARTICLE 2 STATE INSTITUTIONS</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
            <hcontainer GUID="d202cc76-d8dd-4bcd-ae4b-ffc2fcd84bd4" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 1/ARTICLE 2/25-1-201.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-1-201. Establishment of state institutions.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) The following state institutions are established:</p>
                  <p>(i) The Wyoming state penitentiary at Rawlins, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(ii) The Wyoming boys' school at Worland, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(iii) The Wyoming girls' school at Sheridan, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(iv) The Wyoming life resource center at Lander, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(v) Repealed By Laws 1998, ch. 7, \xA7 2.</p>
                  <p>(vi) The Wyoming pioneer home at Thermopolis, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(vii) The veterans' home of Wyoming at Buffalo, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(viii) The Wyoming retirement center at Basin, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(ix) The Wyoming women's center at Lusk, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(x) The Wyoming state hospital at Evanston, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(xi) The Wyoming medium correctional institution at Torrington, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(xii) The Wyoming school for the deaf at Casper, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(xiii) The Wyoming honor farm at Riverton, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(xiv) The Wyoming honor conservation camp at Newcastle, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(xv) The Wyoming veterans' skilled nursing facility at Buffalo, Wyoming.</p>
                  <p>(b) Repealed by Laws 1992, ch. 25, \xA7 4.</p>
                  <p>(c) Repealed by Laws 1992, ch. 25, \xA7 4.</p>
                  <p>(d) Repealed by Laws 1987, ch. 185, \xA7 2.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
        <hcontainer GUID="17231e0a-bdb6-47e6-8460-b381f8510ba0" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 2">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 2 STATE PENITENTIARY</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="2b44d430-4058-45f7-a770-e0960e25219e" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 2/25-2-101.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-2-101. Seal of warden; copies of papers displaying seal received as evidence.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The warden of the penitentiary shall have an official seal bearing the words "Warden of the Penitentiary of the State of Wyoming" of which the courts of this state shall take judicial notice.</p>
                <p>(b) When the official seal of the warden is affixed to copies of papers, books and records kept in his office, the copies are competent evidence in the courts and have the same force and effect as the originals.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="d1b57ca1-a4ac-417a-8120-d86f7e6347ea" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 2/25-2-102.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-2-102. Authority to establish and maintain penitentiary farms; disposition of funds from sales or services; supervision.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The state may establish, maintain and operate one (1) or more penitentiary farms and camps as needed to provide a place of confinement and employment of convicted felons sentenced to the custody of the department of corrections to serve a term of imprisonment in a state penal institution.</p>
                <p>(b) All funds received from the sale of products or services produced on penitentiary farms and camps shall be credited to a separate account.</p>
                <p>(c) All penitentiary farms and camps established shall be operated and maintained under the general supervision of the department of corrections.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="5bfc2f50-70e4-4c95-955d-a1a6ee543c50" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 2/25-2-103.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-2-103. Wyoming women's center; establishment; purpose; supervision.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The Wyoming women's center is established at Lusk, Wyoming, to provide a place of confinement, employment and training for convicted female felons sentenced to the custody of the department of corrections to serve a term of imprisonment in a state penal institution.</p>
                <p>(b) The Wyoming women's center shall be operated and maintained under the general supervision of the department of corrections.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="38726908-7508-473a-a6e5-f0fa221da018" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 2/25-2-104.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-2-104. Wyoming correctional facility; establishment; purpose; supervision.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The Wyoming correctional facility is established at Torrington, Wyoming, to provide a place of confinement, employment and training for convicted felons sentenced to the custody of the department of corrections to serve a term of imprisonment in a state penal institution.</p>
                <p>(b) The Wyoming correctional facility shall be operated and maintained under the general supervision of the department of corrections.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
        <hcontainer GUID="32a56be3-1bac-46f2-89be-d606e9bd90ba" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 3">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 3 WYOMING BOYS' SCHOOL</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="174157d5-b130-48e7-bfc5-4b694e542b04" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 3/25-3-101.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-3-101. Persons to be confined; notice; transportation to school.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) Any boy who has attained the age of twelve (12) years and who has been ordered committed in compliance with W.S. 14-6-229 may be committed to the Wyoming boys' school. The term of any boy committed shall be determined by the department of family services.</p>
                <p>(b) Any person may be sentenced or transferred to the boys' school pursuant to W.S. 7-13-101.</p>
                <p>(c) After a person is committed or sentenced to the Wyoming boys' school the clerk of court shall notify the department of family services and the superintendent of the institution. The department of family services shall arrange for transportation.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="de28bb04-133a-43b4-967f-3a9ed94a9348" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 3/25-3-102.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-3-102. Repealed by Laws 1987, ch. 200, \xA7 1.</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="b4411cd2-54f1-4f22-b9f6-f7f93f591146" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 3/25-3-103.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-3-103. Discipline to be reformatory; employment of residents; sale of products for public use or in open market; disposition of proceeds.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The discipline in the Wyoming boys' school shall be reformatory. Residents of the school may be employed as a means of their support and reformation.</p>
                <p>(b) All articles manufactured and produced, or all agricultural products grown by or through the labor of residents of the school not required for use of the school, may be furnished to:</p>
                <p>(i) The state;</p>
                <p>(ii) Any public institution owned, managed or controlled by the state;</p>
                <p>(iii) The transportation commission for use on any roads or highways;</p>
                <p>(iv) The county authorities of any county.</p>
                <p>(c) The department of family services shall fix the prices of the articles and products which shall be paid upon requisition of the proper officials. The department may sell in the open market or any other manner any or all products grown or produced by residents within or without the boys' school that are not sold for public use.</p>
                <p>(d) All monies received by the department from the sale of products manufactured, produced or grown by the residents of the boys' school shall be deposited in the state treasury and credited to the general fund.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="a933c02a-e0c9-4f2b-be8a-fde6a50d405f" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 3/25-3-104.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-3-104. Transfer of residents to state hospital; rules and regulations governing residents.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The department of family services may, with the approval of the department of health, transfer any resident who becomes mentally incompetent to any appropriate acute placement facility based on a psychiatric evaluation.</p>
                <p>(b) The department shall make all rules and regulations necessary and proper for:</p>
                <p>(i) Employment, discipline, instruction and education of residents;</p>
                <p>(ii) Mental and physical health and welfare of residents;</p>
                <p>(iii) Transfer and return of residents; and</p>
                <p>(iv) Work release for residents who are not subject to home visitation or temporary residence outside the school enclosure.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="bf98d19d-6bda-4675-8ad4-077ce8465988" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 3/25-3-105.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-3-105. Control over residents; preparation of personal record; rehabilitation plan and periodic reviews thereof; contents of record.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>The department of family services shall maintain control over all persons committed to the boys' school to prevent the persons from committing crime, best secure their self-support and accomplish their reformation. When a person is admitted to the school, the superintendent shall prepare a record of the personal history of the resident, including his age, family and social background, education and prior training and employment. Based upon all pertinent information available, the superintendent shall prepare an individualized rehabilitation plan which shall be part of the resident's record. Periodic reviews of the resident's progress and appropriate modifications of his rehabilitation plan shall be made by the superintendent and entered on the resident's record. The status of each resident shall be reported to him periodically. All orders affecting the resident, the circumstance of his final release and any new developments concerning his personal history shall be included in his record.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="95f9c908-46b2-4fd2-952e-0583ac875f66" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 3/25-3-106.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-3-106. Release of resident.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>After the department of family services has made a finding that a boy should be released from the Wyoming boys' school, it shall give advance notification of the pending release to the court which ordered commitment. Upon the boy's release the department shall issue him an administrative discharge.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
        <hcontainer GUID="4388d203-8a7c-4211-b5c9-18d7494ce5af" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 4">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 4 WYOMING GIRLS' SCHOOL</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="31e271ca-7c1f-471c-b383-cbabf303dd57" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 4/25-4-101.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-4-101. Girls to be committed; terms; notification of superintendent; transportation to school.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) Any girl who has attained the age of twelve (12) years and who has been ordered committed in compliance with W.S. 14-6-229 may be committed to the Wyoming girls' school. The term of any girl committed shall be determined by the department of family services.</p>
                <p>(b) After a girl is committed to the girls' school the clerk of court shall notify the superintendent of the institution. The superintendent shall arrange for the transportation of the girl to the girls' school.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="f60155f0-f9d5-4266-bf83-d72889c19b1d" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 4/25-4-102.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-4-102. Nature of program and discipline; rules and regulations for work release, home visitation or temporary residence.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>The program and discipline at the Wyoming girls' school shall be educational, vocational and rehabilitative. For these purposes the department of family services shall adopt rules and regulations for work release for residents who are not subject to home visitation or temporary residence outside the school enclosure.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="3e451397-ce3b-4876-a3d4-eb5f0a502b0a" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 4/25-4-103.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-4-103. Personal record to be prepared; rehabilitation plan; periodic review; additional contents of record; release from custody.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) When a girl is admitted to the girls' school, the superintendent shall prepare a record of the personal history of the resident, including her age, family and social background, education and prior training and employment. Based upon all pertinent information available, the superintendent shall prepare an individualized rehabilitation plan which shall be part of the resident's record. Periodic reviews of the resident's progress and appropriate modifications of her rehabilitation plan shall be made by the superintendent and entered on the resident's record. The status of each resident shall be reported to her periodically. All orders affecting the resident, the circumstances of her final release and any new developments concerning her personal history shall be included in her record.</p>
                <p>(b) After the department of family services has made a finding that a girl should be released from the girls' school, it shall give advance notification of the pending release to the court which ordered commitment. Upon the girl's release the department shall issue her an administrative discharge.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
        <hcontainer GUID="43a22e7f-6714-4202-81d5-02a6789ac383" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 5 LIFE RESOURCE CENTER</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="c0e8fefd-16db-4232-a5a5-f8d3911c3aa3" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-101.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-101. Short title.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>This act may be cited as the "Life Resource Center Act".</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="5386eacc-a4e4-4b26-baf0-8f0f1d59e900" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-102.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-102. Definitions.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) Repealed By Laws 2008, Ch. 70, \xA7 2, Ch. 85, \xA7 2.</p>
                <p>(b) As used in this act:</p>
                <p>(i) "Acquired brain injury" means any combination of focal and diffuse central nervous system dysfunction, at the brain stem level and above, acquired after birth through the interaction of any external forces and the body, oxygen deprivation, infection, toxicity, surgery or vascular disorders not associated with aging;</p>
                <p>(ii) "Active treatment" means a program which includes aggressive, consistent implementation of a program of specialized and generic training, treatment, health services and related services that is directed toward:</p>
                <p>(A) The acquisition of the behaviors necessary for the client to function with as much self determination and independence as possible; and</p>
                <p>(B) The prevention or deceleration of regression or loss of current optimal functional status.</p>
                <p>(iii) "Adaptive behavior" means the collection of conceptual, social and practical skills that have been learned by people in order to function in their everyday lives;</p>
                <p>(iv) "Administrator" means the administrator of the division;</p>
                <p>(v) "Assistive technology device" and "assistive technology service" mean as defined in 42 U.S.C. 15002;</p>
                <p>(vi) "Center" means the Wyoming life resource center at Lander, Wyoming;</p>
                <p>(vii) "Child" means any person under the age of eighteen (18);</p>
                <p>(viii) "Client" means a person who has a disability and has been determined eligible, pursuant to department rules and regulation, and is receiving services from one (1) of the center's programs;</p>
                <p>(ix) "Client services" means diagnosis, education, training and care of persons who have been admitted to the center;</p>
                <p>(x) "Conservator" means as defined in W.S. 3-1-101(a)(iii);</p>
                <p>(xi) "Department" means the state department of health;</p>
                <p>(xii) "Director" means the director of the department of health;</p>
                <p>(xiii) "Disability" means a developmental disability as defined in 42 U.S.C. 15002 or a disability resulting from an acquired brain injury;</p>
                <p>(xiv) "Division" means the behavioral health division of the department of health;</p>
                <p>(xv) "Guardian" means as defined in W.S. 3-1-101(a)(v);</p>
                <p>(xvi) "Guardian ad litem" means as defined in W.S. 3-1-101(a)(vi);</p>
                <p>(xvii) "Incompetent person" means adjudicated as meeting the definition in W.S. 3-1-101(a)(ix);</p>
                <p>(xviii) "Individual program plan" means a written statement of long-term and short-term goals and strategies for providing specially designed services to meet each client's individual educational, physical, emotional and training needs;</p>
                <p>(xix) "Informed choice" means making a decision based on adequate information. As appropriate, such information may include consideration regarding providers, methods, costs, duration, accessibility, customer satisfaction, probabilities, sources and consequences;</p>
                <p>(xx) "Intellectual disability" means significantly subaverage general intellectual functioning with concurrent deficits in adaptive behavior manifested during the developmental period. "Intellectually disabled" means a person with an intellectual disability;</p>
                <p>(xxi) "Interdisciplinary team" means a group that represents the person, the person's family or guardian, or the professions, disciplines or service areas that are relevant to identifying the client's needs, as described in the comprehensive functional assessments and program design. The department shall provide by rule and regulation for the composition of interdisciplinary teams;</p>
                <p>(xxii) "Intermediate care facility for people with intellectual disability" means an intermediate care facility for individuals with intellectual disabilities (ICF/IID), as this phrase is used in applicable federal statutes, rules and regulations;</p>
                <p>(xxiii) "Least restrictive environment" means the program, service and location which least inhibits a person's freedom of movement, informed decision making and participation in community life while achieving the purposes of habilitation and treatment which best meet the needs of the person. The determination of least restrictive environment shall be individualized, based on a person's need for medical, therapeutic, rehabilitative and developmental services and as a result of informed choice of the person or, if the person is a minor or a ward, his parent or guardian;</p>
                <p>(xxiv) "Most appropriate" means an individualized determination of a person's need for medical, therapeutic, rehabilitative and developmental services, based upon professional assessment and the informed choice of the person or, if the person is a minor or ward, his parent or guardian;</p>
                <p>(xxv) "Most integrated" means the setting that enables a person with a disability to have access to the same opportunities as a person without a disability to the fullest extent possible, including opportunities to live, learn, work, recreate and participate in family and community activities. Determinations of most integrated shall be individualized and based upon professional assessment and the informed choice of the person or, if the person is a minor or ward, his parent or guardian;</p>
                <p>(xxvi) "Program manager" means the on-site supervisor and manager of the center;</p>
                <p>(xxvii) "Screening team" means a group of appropriate professionals, appointed by the director pursuant to rules and regulations of the department, and assigned by the administrator to perform preliminary testing and assessment of persons for purposes of determining eligibility for services at the center;</p>
                <p>(xxviii) "Ward" means as defined in W.S. 3-1-101(a)(xv);</p>
                <p>(xxix) "This act" means W.S. 25 5 101 through 25 5 135;</p>
                <p>(xxx) "Domiciliary care" means the domiciliary care program, as defined by applicable federal statutes, rules and regulations;</p>
                <p>(xxxi) "Exceptionally difficult behaviors" means a high level of assaultive or self-injurious behavior in a person with an intellectual disability or organic brain syndrome. These behaviors may include aggression and violent behavior, wandering, sexually inappropriate behavior, self-endangering behaviors or medication noncompliance. The level of behaviors shall be measured by a standardized assessment and pursuant to criteria established by the department under W.S. 25-5-105(a)(i);</p>
                <p>(xxxii) "Hard to place" means a person who is:</p>
                <p>(A) Eligible for skilled nursing facility services pursuant to the long-term care assessment defined in W.S. 42-6-102(a)(vii);</p>
                <p>(B) Does not meet the criteria of paragraph (xxxi), (xxxiii) or (xxxiv) of this subsection; and</p>
                <p>(C) For whom no community skilled nursing facility service provider has been identified in the state within a time period defined by the department.</p>
                <p>(xxxiii) "High medical need" means a person who is:</p>
                <p>(A) Eligible for skilled nursing facility services pursuant to the long term care assessment defined in W.S. 42-6-102(a)(vii);</p>
                <p>(B) Does not meet the criteria of paragraph</p>
                <p>(xxxi) or (xxxiv) of this subsection; and</p>
                <p>(C) Would qualify for the extraordinary care nursing facility reimbursement rate, as defined by the department.</p>
                <p>(xxxiv) "Organic brain syndrome" means a decrease in mental function due to a medical disease, other than mental illness, as defined by the department. Organic brain syndrome may be the result of an acquired brain injury or the result of dementia caused by trauma, hypoxia, cardiovascular conditions including thrombotic and embolic events or degenerative, infectious, alcohol and drug related or metabolic disorders;</p>
                <p>(xxxv) "Skilled nursing facility services" means skilled nursing facility services as defined by applicable federal statutes, rules and regulations.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="25e78ced-1918-4e2e-926b-ce1cec61acd3" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-103.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-103. Wyoming life resource center established; purpose.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) Except as otherwise authorized by rules and regulations promulgated in accordance with W.S. 9-2-106(d), the Wyoming life resource center is established to provide the following residential, active treatment, assistive technology, medical and therapy services only to individuals for whom an interdisciplinary team has determined the center is the most appropriate, least restrictive and most integrated environment for delivery of the services as specified below:</p>
                <p>(i) Intermediate care facilities for people with intellectual disability in accordance with federal Medicare and Medicaid regulations;</p>
                <p>(ii) Skilled nursing facility services to the following:</p>
                <p>(A) Persons with organic brain syndrome who manifest exceptionally difficult behaviors;</p>
                <p>(B) Persons with high medical need;</p>
                <p>(C) Persons who are hard to place.</p>
                <p>(iii) Disability, therapeutic and assistive technology services for persons with a disability;</p>
                <p>(iv) Training for state employees, other service providers and caregivers on disability, medical, developmental and therapy services;</p>
                <p>(v) Care provided under authority of the director pursuant to W.S. 9-2-106(d).</p>
                <p>(b) The Wyoming life resource center may provide technical assistance and assistive technology outreach services to persons made eligible pursuant to rules adopted by the department.</p>
                <p>(c) Any person residing at the Wyoming life resource center on April 1, 2016 pursuant to the requirements of this section prior to April 1, 2016 shall have the right to remain at the life resource center without regard to his continued qualification to remain at the center under this section, provided the center continues to have adequate resources to safely care for the person.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="47d286c4-0a43-4b74-b17e-a8784a5e4865" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-104.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-104. Administration and management of center.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>The administration and management of the center is vested in the department.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="d3a90e3f-40ca-4aea-939c-f0f38049f8e0" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-105.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-105. Rules and regulations; reports.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The department shall adopt rules and regulations which are in compliance with both federal regulations for intermediate care facilities for persons with intellectual disability and federal regulations for skilled nursing facilities, and which:</p>
                <p>(i) Establish standards for admission for residential services and discharge of clients receiving services in all programs administered by the center;</p>
                <p>(ii) Establish standards for client services;</p>
                <p>(iii) Provide for the administration of the center under the management of the division;</p>
                <p>(iv) Prescribe professional standards for personnel employed at the center;</p>
                <p>(v) Implement this act;</p>
                <p>(vi) Establish data reporting processes and report monthly to the director the number of persons served by the center, identified by service category, and the services provided to those persons.</p>
                <p>(b) Repealed by Laws 2015, ch. 59, \xA7 2.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="7dc3c27a-ba05-4e1d-85ca-dccade6f656f" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-106.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-106. Donations for benefit of center; control and disposition thereof.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>Money, personal property or real estate donated for the benefit of the center shall be held, controlled and distributed by the department according to the conditions of the donation. If there are no conditions of the donation, it shall be disposed of as provided in W.S. 25-5-107.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="72dc82db-5911-4caf-a962-a71b89d790c5" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-107.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-107. Disposition of monies received from sale of products or as compensation.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>Except as provided by W.S. 25-5-106, all monies received by the department for the clients in the center from the sale of products produced or grown by the center or as compensation from any source shall be deposited in the state treasury and credited to the general fund.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="afcf620b-77e1-4602-82d4-2123f0497db1" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-108.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-108. Appointment of program manager; duties; removal.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The director shall appoint a program manager of the center.</p>
                <p>(b) The program manager shall administer the center as directed by the administrator.</p>
                <p>(c) The director may remove the program manager in his discretion.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="da17db5f-b21e-441c-833d-974ff5d52494" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-109.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-109. Inability or refusal to pay for services.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</p>
                <p>(b) Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</p>
                <p>(c) No person shall be denied admission to or services by the center because of the inability of the person, his parent or guardian to pay the cost of the services received.</p>
                <p>(d) Clients of the center who are not eligible under the Wyoming Medical Assistance and Services Act shall be responsible for the cost of services and treatment as provided in title 25, chapter 11, article 1. However, no person who was a client of the center as of June 30, 2008 shall be denied admission to or services by the center because of the refusal of the client's parent or guardian to pay the cost of the services received.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="0ea0fb2d-7416-4fc7-8c38-2f949c7bf10b" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-110.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-110. Special education for minors and costs thereof.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) Repealed by Laws 1986, ch. 25, \xA7 3.</p>
                <p>(b) Repealed by Laws 1986, ch. 25, \xA7 3.</p>
                <p>(c) Clients who are between the ages of five (5) and twenty-one (21) years of age shall be provided special education and related services through the clients' resident school districts. This subsection does not relieve an insurer or similar third party from an otherwise valid obligation to pay for services provided to the client.</p>
                <p>(d) Repealed by Laws 1986, ch. 25, \xA7 3.</p>
                <p>(e) Repealed by Laws 1986, ch. 25, \xA7 3.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="32f418fa-d03a-4cc3-87e4-5bd7c61bf576" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-111.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-111. Repealed by Laws 1986, ch. 25, \xA7 3.</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="85dc0cd1-0038-4b67-83f1-3a008a452def" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-112.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-112. Repealed by Laws 1986, ch. 25, \xA7 3.</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="f65a42ae-3544-4fb8-b963-9ff8e5a31e4a" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-113.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-113. Repealed by Laws 1986, ch. 25, \xA7 3.</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="c8b9f56e-604c-42a0-a776-fc952d6c8917" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-114.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-114. Eligibility for admission; appropriateness of services.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) Except as otherwise authorized by rules and regulations promulgated in accordance with W.S. 9-2-106(d), a person shall be admitted to the center only if he is an individual qualifying for services under W.S. 25-5-103(a) and his preadmission evaluation and screening does not indicate that he would be more appropriately served by the Wyoming state hospital, a community program or a public school program.</p>
                <p>(b) Repealed By Laws 2008, Ch. 85, \xA7 2.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="a293f543-7b9e-490d-8cca-c618883bd51e" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-115.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-115. Preadmission screening for residential services; preparation and supervision thereof; disposition of findings.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) Admission to the center shall be upon written application to the division and shall be based upon the preadmission screening and assessment:</p>
                <p>(i) The preadmission screening and assessment shall be made by a screening team under the supervision of the administrator or his designee, using appropriate professionals and screening and assessment methods as provided in department rules and regulations;</p>
                <p>(ii) The preadmission screening and assessment shall be completed not more than thirty (30) days after an application for admission;</p>
                <p>(iii) Repealed by Laws 2016, ch. 44, \xA7 2.</p>
                <p>(iv) As part of the application process, division staff shall provide prospective clients and their families or guardians information about center services and similar services available in the client's community or elsewhere in the state.</p>
                <p>(b) Within ten (10) days of completion of the preadmission screening and assessment, the findings shall be given to the applicant. If ordered by the court, the preadmission screening and assessment shall also be filed with the court.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="be1eebea-3289-4f25-ad96-2073c326c662" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-116.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-116. Individual program plan; preparation and supervision thereof; review.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>Each client admitted to the center shall have on file at the center an individual program plan. The individual program plans shall be prepared by an interdisciplinary team within thirty (30) days of admission for residential services under the supervision of the program manager. The plan shall be reviewed by the interdisciplinary team for appropriateness and feasibility of discharge or transition to another level of service thirty (30) days after implementation of the plan, at the end of each quarter for the first year and annually thereafter.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="be613bed-437c-4464-af1d-20d4f9839273" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-117.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-117. Admission for residential services; application and contents thereof; written copy of rights; appeal of denied admissions.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) A person determined by the preadmission screening and assessment to be eligible for admission to the center for residential services may be admitted as a client under one (1) of the following procedures:</p>
                <p>(i) An adult who has sufficient insight or capacity to make responsible application for admission for residential services may be admitted on his own application;</p>
                <p>(ii) A minor or ward may be admitted upon application of his parent or guardian.</p>
                <p>(b) Repealed By Laws 2008, Ch. 85, \xA7 2.</p>
                <p>(c) At the time of admission for residential services, the program manager shall give a written copy of the rights provided in W.S. 25-5-132 to the client, his parent or guardian.</p>
                <p>(d) A person who is denied admission may appeal the decision to the department, in writing.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="03c0f78b-469f-40ff-9571-54cd293f3ee9" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-118.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-118. Release of voluntary client upon request; exceptions.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) A voluntary client may be discharged by the administrator at any time within twenty (20) days of receipt of a written request for the release by the client, his parent or guardian, and the administrator shall arrange for appropriate transition services, except:</p>
                <p>(i) If the client was admitted on his own application and the request for discharge is made by a person other than the client, release shall be conditioned upon the client's consent;</p>
                <p>(ii) If the client is a minor or ward, his discharge shall be conditioned upon the consent of his parent or guardian;</p>
                <p>(iii) If the administrator has probable cause to believe release of the client will endanger the life, health or safety of the client or others and he incorporates a written statement of the facts supporting his belief in the client's file, he may apply for involuntary admission pursuant to W.S. 25-5-119. The administrator, as a mandatory reporter, shall contact adult protective services for appropriate proceedings.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="7347b42c-74b0-4cdc-9f12-fec1efac5a0e" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-119.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-119. Involuntary admissions; application to district court; representation of proposed client; preadmission screening; notice; hearing; independent screening; admissibility.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) A person may be an involuntary client of the center if admitted pursuant to this section. Application for involuntary admission may be made by a parent, a guardian, the administrator or a social service agency. The application shall be filed with the district court in the county where the proposed client, his parent or his guardian resides.</p>
                <p>(b) When an application for involuntary admission is filed, the court shall appoint an attorney to represent the proposed client unless he retains counsel of his own choice. An attorney shall represent the proposed client at all hearings. The county shall compensate an appointed attorney in an amount fixed by the court as a reasonable fee.</p>
                <p>(c) The court shall order the center to conduct a preadmission screening and assessment of the proposed client. Notice of the order shall be served on the proposed client, his attorney and his parent or guardian. The order and the application for admission shall be served on the center and the department. If the preadmission screening and assessment report finds the center would be an appropriate placement, the court shall order a hearing. The proposed client shall have a right to seek an independent screening and assessment of his eligibility for admission at the state's expense. The screening and assessment shall be admissible as evidence at the hearing as provided by W.S. 25-5-121(d).</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="e8fda4e7-e6ad-4de0-a743-ec6c344f9114" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-120.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-120. Court order setting hearing on involuntary application; service of notice; waiver.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The court shall fix a date for hearing on the application.</p>
                <p>(b) The order setting the hearing shall contain:</p>
                <p>(i) The date, time and place of the hearing;</p>
                <p>(ii) The name and address of the applicant, the proposed client's parent or guardian, and the attorney retained by the proposed client or appointed by the court;</p>
                <p>(iii) The grounds alleged for the commitment of the proposed client;</p>
                <p>(iv) The consequences of a finding that a person shall be admitted to the center for client services.</p>
                <p>(c) The court shall direct the clerk of the district court to give notice to each person named in the order:</p>
                <p>(i) By delivering a copy of the notice to the person being notified personally, not less than fourteen (14) days before the time set for hearing unless time is shortened by the court for good cause shown; or</p>
                <p>(ii) By mailing a copy of the notice to the address of each person given in the application by certified mail, return receipt requested, not less than fourteen (14) days before the time set for hearing, unless the time is shortened by the court for good cause shown.</p>
                <p>(d) The court may order that notice be given to other persons. Notice may be waived in writing by any party except the proposed client's attorney.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="343e4ede-c5fe-4903-9b4e-e876afd135a8" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-121.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-121. Rights of proposed client and notified persons; confidentiality of hearing; admissibility of screening reports; findings by court or jury; amendment of admission order.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The proposed client has the right to appear, to be heard and to participate in every stage of the hearing unless the court finds that it would not be in the best interests of the proposed client. The court shall not exclude the proposed client from the hearing unless the application is accompanied by a written statement from a licensed physician and a court designated examiner, appointed at the time of the application, who is in no other manner involved in the proceedings, that attendance at the hearing would injure the proposed client's health and well-being and describing his medical condition.</p>
                <p>(b) The proposed client is entitled, upon request, to a jury trial on the issue of his admission. The jury shall be selected pursuant to W.S. 1-11-101 through 1-11-129.</p>
                <p>(c) The court shall exclude all persons not having an interest in the application. Unless the court orders an open hearing or the proposed client requests a jury trial, the hearing is confidential and shall be held in closed court.</p>
                <p>(d) Any person to whom notice is required to be given by W.S. 25-5-120 may testify and may present and cross-examine witnesses. The court may receive the testimony of other persons in its discretion. The screening and assessment report required by W.S. 25-5-115, and any independent screening and assessment made under W.S. 25-5-119, may be admitted as evidence and shall not be excluded on the ground of hearsay alone.</p>
                <p>(e) If the court or jury finds that specific care, treatment and service alternatives are available which are more appropriate than the center for the proposed client, the application shall be denied. If the court or jury finds by clear and convincing evidence that admission to the center would provide the most appropriate services for the proposed client, the court shall order the admission. In case of a nonjury hearing, the court shall enter findings of fact with the order of admission.</p>
                <p>(f) The proposed client or if a minor or ward, his parents or guardian or the center may petition the court to amend its order of admission on the grounds that appropriate and necessary services to the proposed client are available in a less restrictive environment than the center. The court may amend its order after notice and hearing pursuant to this act.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="1e0e2d1a-5805-47e4-905b-71a2b132e86f" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-122.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-122. Appeals to supreme court; rules governing.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>Any person aggrieved by any order entered under this act may appeal to the Wyoming supreme court. The appeal shall conform with the rules of civil procedure.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="3478b7c2-a9d9-431b-98a6-3b1c84e63d16" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-123.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-123. Repealed By Laws 2008, Ch. 85, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="0b6ef751-cf8c-487e-aeaf-9ba4bc942beb" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-124.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-124. Discharge of clients by administrator or by court; appeals to department.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) An interdisciplinary team may recommend to the administrator discharge of a client with an appropriate transition plan from the center when placement at home, with another service provider or another program is appropriate for the client's needs and abilities. The transition plan shall identify any recommended discharge conditions in the client's best interest, including type of residence facility, supervision and any continuing medical, therapeutic, rehabilitative or developmental services. Based on the recommendations of the team, and with the consent of the client, or his parent or guardian if he is a minor or ward, the administrator shall place the client in the alternative setting. The administrator shall discharge the client when the client has been appropriately placed in an alternative program. If the client was admitted under a court order, the administrator shall petition the court, pursuant to W.S. 25-5-121(f).</p>
                <p>(b) If the client, or his parent or guardian if he is a minor or incompetent, disagrees with the decision of the administrator and the interdisciplinary team, the client, parent or guardian may appeal the decision to the director in writing. The department shall provide the client, parent or guardian with a decision in writing within thirty (30) days.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="9e48fd4c-b53f-4f42-8371-66108d5ffc6b" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-125.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-125. Transfer of clients for temporary care and treatment; consent; costs to be paid by center; third-party obligations not limited.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>If the program manager determines it is appropriate for the welfare of a client, the client may be placed for temporary care and treatment in any public or private hospital, institution or residence in the state which provides services which will benefit the client. The transfer shall not be made without the consent of the client and his parents or guardian, or in the case of an involuntary client, without leave of the court, except in cases of medical emergency. During and after the transfer, the client remains a client of the center. The cost of the transfer and of the temporary treatment, care and training provided shall be borne by the center. This section does not limit the responsibility of third parties to pay for medical and other expenses incurred by contract or law.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="54f74e8e-7001-4647-b0b9-420d7e970e4a" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-126.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-126. Contracts with other states for interstate transfer of clients; payment of expenses therefor.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The department may enter into contracts with other states to provide for:</p>
                <p>(i) The admission to facilities, schools or hospitals in other states of persons admitted to or entitled to admission for residential services in the center, when it can be shown that admission to a facility in another state is in the best interests of the person and the state of Wyoming;</p>
                <p>(ii) The admission to the center of residents of other states when it can be shown that admission to the center for residential services is in the best interests of the person and the state of Wyoming, and that the person's need for services has been determined in accordance with this act.</p>
                <p>(b) The expense of transferring persons from the center to other states shall be paid by the center. The expense of transferring persons from other states to the center shall be paid by the state making the transfer to the center.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="c84f08a2-667f-42eb-9f39-0c1c80703462" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-127.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-127. Repealed By Laws 2008, Ch. 85, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="fc6d73fc-599d-4e97-b701-4c4b7e87d717" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-128.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-128. Repealed By Laws 2008, Ch. 85, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="179a1b99-6077-4e1d-b0f8-255720a72379" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-129.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-129. Admittance for temporary services; excepted provisions; limited duration.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>The administrator may admit individuals for services temporarily pursuant to rules promulgated under W.S. 25-5-105(a) if the administrator determines a less restrictive environment is appropriate but unavailable. A client admitted for services temporarily is not subject to W.S. 25-5-114, 25-5-115 and 25-5-121(e). No individual shall be admitted temporarily for services for more than seventy-five (75) days.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="9bff13c9-0fc6-4eb9-b56a-69f89778b8e5" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-130.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-130. Consent and notice required before major surgery; exceptions.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) Except as provided in subsection (b) of this section, no client shall undergo major surgery until the superintendent:</p>
                <p>(i) Obtains the prior consent of the client, or if his consent cannot be given knowingly, he shall obtain the prior consent of the resident's parent or guardian; and</p>
                <p>(ii) Notifies the parent or guardian of the nature, date and place of the surgery and the name of the surgeon. A copy of the notice shall be placed in the patient's records.</p>
                <p>(b) Prior consent need not be obtained nor prior notice given when the parent or guardian cannot be located or when an emergency requires immediate surgery to prevent serious consequences or death. The parent or guardian shall be notified as soon as possible after emergency surgery.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="b0ef156d-d767-4ca6-87f3-4863c2142071" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-131.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-131. Confidentiality of records; exceptions; penalties for violations.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) All records of clients, former clients and proposed clients of the center are confidential except as provided by subsection (b) of this section, when disclosure is required by state or federal law or when disclosure is necessary to prevent imminent risk of harm to the person who is the subject of the records or others.</p>
                <p>(b) The administrator may provide access to the records of a client, former client or proposed client by:</p>
                <p>(i) The person who is the subject of the records or his guardian, guardian ad litem or attorney;</p>
                <p>(ii) The physician or surgeon for the person who is the subject of the records;</p>
                <p>(iii) A person authorized by the person who is the subject of the records, or by his parent or guardian if he is a minor or ward, to evaluate the person's eligibility for admission to the center for residential services or to determine whether his residence is the most appropriate and therapeutic environment for the person;</p>
                <p>(iv) A court, upon a showing that access to the records is necessary for the determination of an issue before it. Access under this paragraph is limited to an in camera inspection unless the court finds public disclosure is necessary;</p>
                <p>(v) Qualified employees of the department and the center and professional persons while in the performance of their official duties;</p>
                <p>(vi) A person as required by law, including the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act and the Medicaid program.</p>
                <p>(c) Repealed By Laws 2008, Ch. 85, \xA7 2.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="2b0e529a-6a5d-4cea-bf66-8b1d6f3cee5d" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-132.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-132. No determination of incompetency; notification of rights; deniable rights and conditions therefor; undeniable rights.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The determination that a person is eligible for admission to the center is not a determination or adjudication that the person is incompetent.</p>
                <p>(b) Upon admission to the center for residential services, a client shall be informed orally and in writing of his rights under this section. If the client is a minor, or ward, his parents, guardian or guardian ad litem shall be informed orally and in writing of his rights under this section.</p>
                <p>(c) The following rights of a client may be denied or limited only as a part of his individual program plan for purposes of safety and health. The client or if the client is a minor or ward, his parents, guardian or guardian ad litem shall be informed in writing and orally of the grounds for the denial or limitation. The grounds for denial or limitation shall be entered in the individual program plan:</p>
                <p>(i) The right to send and receive unopened mail;</p>
                <p>(ii) The right to choose and wear his own clothing;</p>
                <p>(iii) The right to keep and use his own personal possessions including his toilet articles;</p>
                <p>(iv) The right to keep and spend his own money;</p>
                <p>(v) The right to be free from physical restraints and chemical restraints that substitute for active treatment or behavior modification programs, except in emergency situations as necessary to protect the client or others;</p>
                <p>(vi) The right to privacy in matters such as toileting and bathing;</p>
                <p>(vii) The right to make and receive telephone calls;</p>
                <p>(viii) The right to receive visitors daily;</p>
                <p>(ix) The right to an appropriate personal space that provides privacy and personal safety;</p>
                <p>(x) The right to be free from abuse;</p>
                <p>(xi) The right to vote;</p>
                <p>(xii) The right to choose where and with whom to live;</p>
                <p>(xiii) The right to present grievances and complaints or to request changes in policies and services without restraint, interference, coercion, discrimination or reprisal;</p>
                <p>(xiv) The right to participate or refuse to participate in religious worship;</p>
                <p>(xv) The right to the least restrictive environment.</p>
                <p>(d) A client may not be denied the following rights unless the denial is authorized by a court, the client or, if the client is a minor or ward, his parent or guardian:</p>
                <p>(i) The right to be free from unnecessary or excessive medication;</p>
                <p>(ii) The right to refuse to be subjected to experimental medical or psychological research without the express and informed consent of the client or his parent or guardian if he is a minor or ward. The client or his parent or guardian may consult with independent medical or psychological specialists and his attorney before consenting or refusing;</p>
                <p>(iii) The right to refuse to be subjected to drastic treatment procedures without the express and informed consent of the client and his parent or guardian if he is a minor or ward.</p>
                <p>(iv) Repealed By Laws 2008, Ch. 85, \xA7 2.</p>
                <p>(v) Repealed By Laws 2008, Ch. 85, \xA7 2.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="85d248f0-4906-4492-bfbc-53fab0c57fad" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-133.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-133. Restraint; conditions for use; strict administration of medication; prohibited uses.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) Isolation or seclusion procedures in which a person is placed alone in a locked room or in an area from which the person is physically prevented from leaving are prohibited. Restraint of a client shall be used only when less restrictive measures are ineffective for the welfare of the client or others and only when necessary to ensure the immediate physical safety of the client or others. Restraint shall be used in a manner which ensures that the dignity and safety of the person restrained are protected and shall be regularly monitored by trained staff. The reason for restrictive measures shall be reported in the client's records and shall be reviewed by the interdisciplinary team and program manager. In addition, the client's individual program plan shall address active treatment or less restrictive measures to manage or eliminate the behaviors for which restraint was used.</p>
                <p>(b) Medication shall be administered to a client only pursuant to the order of a medical professional acting within the scope of his license. A record of the medication, the dosage administered, the date and the person administering the medication to each client shall be kept in each client's treatment record. Medication shall not be used as punishment, for the convenience of staff or in quantities that interfere with a client's treatment program.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="1c519c0d-467f-41ce-a998-a81e68d86786" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-134.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-134. Employment of clients within institution; wages; duties; discharge for cause.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>Clients who are employed within the center shall be paid a reasonable wage based upon commensurate wages under special certificate as authorized by the federal Fair Labor Standards Act at 21 U.S.C. 214(c). The program manager shall prescribe for each position a written job description with wages, benefits and job duties clearly defined. The employment relationship pursuant to this section shall be at will.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="12ab2469-8e0d-46c6-a280-7e753c6c6901" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 5/25-5-135.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-5-135. Medications aides.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>Any person trained and qualified as a medication aide may administer medications in basic client care situations at the center. The center shall develop curricula, certification criteria and protocols concerning administration of medications and use of medication aides. Every medication aide shall perform the duties authorized under this section under the direction of a person licensed by the laws of this state to administer medications. The direction of medication aides shall not constitute an unlawful delegation of professional duties by the licensed nurse or other professional licensed to administer medications.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
        <hcontainer GUID="9bd52b01-2954-4af0-8190-948108d6a2ab" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 6">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 6 GIFTS FOR THE BLIND</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="1e77f779-7ad0-4c0c-a5b2-d424f5c7f2f2" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 6/25-6-101.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-6-101. Authority of state to receive property; maintenance; sale and investment of proceeds.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The state may receive gifts, devises, bequests, deeds and other conveyances of property of any kind for the benefit of the blind citizens of Wyoming.</p>
                <p>(b) The property received shall be cared for and may be sold and the proceeds invested for the benefit of the visually handicapped citizens of Wyoming. The state department of education shall act for the state as the custodian of all property received under this section and shall promulgate rules and regulations for the administration of the property and all proceeds for the benefit of the visually handicapped citizens of Wyoming.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
        <hcontainer GUID="efd99795-cde3-4857-aed6-f0fe932559da" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 7">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 7 WYOMING YOUTH TREATMENT CENTER</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="917a29ca-e301-4068-b46b-b1fc27860792" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 7/25-7-101.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-7-101. Repealed By Laws 1998, ch. 7, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="6efbf699-252e-4cf2-984b-2ee534fb7763" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 7/25-7-102.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-7-102. Repealed by Laws 1986, ch. 25, \xA7 3.</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
        <hcontainer GUID="a70bf5eb-b48b-4747-98e9-bab27c0673d3" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 8">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 8 WYOMING PIONEER HOME AND WYOMING RETIREMENT CENTER</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="ce1a7c46-cde9-47f5-95b6-2c482014f789" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 8/25-8-101.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-8-101. Purpose.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>Except as otherwise authorized by rules and regulations promulgated in accordance with W.S. 9-2-106(d), the purpose of the pioneer home and the Wyoming retirement center is to provide a place for the care and maintenance of residents of this state who are afflicted with the infirmities of old age.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="46213de0-75cd-4a34-8385-3836301e415e" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 8/25-8-102.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-8-102. Powers and duties of department of health.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The department of health may:</p>
                <p>(i) Construct, maintain, equip, operate and manage the pioneer home and the Wyoming retirement center;</p>
                <p>(ii) Purchase, rent or otherwise provide the equipment, materials or supplies necessary to carry out the purposes hereof;</p>
                <p>(iii) Dispose of equipment, materials and supplies no longer required in the operations of the pioneer home or the Wyoming retirement center;</p>
                <p>(iv) Adopt rules and regulations for the admission, conduct and discharge of residents;</p>
                <p>(v) Accept gifts on behalf of the state for the use of the pioneer home and the Wyoming retirement center;</p>
                <p>(vi) Provide medical care for residents of the Wyoming retirement center.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="66aeb704-5d87-42df-a8b9-49c5f1521f83" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 8/25-8-103.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-8-103. Conditions for admission; charges for care.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>Admission to the pioneer home and the Wyoming retirement center shall be voluntary and only upon prior approval by the department of health. Indigent aged persons may be cared for without charge. Nonindigent aged persons may be cared for under terms and conditions fixed by the department pursuant to W.S. 25-11-101 through 25-11-108.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="ad8b55c0-7725-4c72-9588-76c2ac15f475" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 8/25-8-104.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-8-104. Receipt and disposition of revenues and gifts.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) All revenues received from the operation of the pioneer home and from gifts given for the general purpose of the pioneer home shall be paid over to the state treasurer and deposited in the general fund. Gifts given for a specific purpose shall be kept in a separate account to be expended by the department of health for the specific purpose.</p>
                <p>(b) The department shall deposit all funds received, collected by or donated to the Wyoming retirement center for care of patients into the special revenue fund. The funds collected are appropriated to the department and shall only be expended to fund the operation of the Wyoming retirement center and shall be disbursed pursuant to W.S. 9-4-304.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
        <hcontainer GUID="16e38a97-2595-4e0e-9978-aa27ce6082ef" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 9">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 9 VETERANS' HOME OF WYOMING</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="97081efc-a69f-4512-a6ec-c84b4447fc68" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 9/25-9-101.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-9-101. Purpose; admission of veterans and veterans' dependents.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) Except as otherwise authorized by rules and regulations promulgated in accordance with W.S. 9-2-106(d), the veterans' home of Wyoming shall provide domiciliary level care and, if appropriate facilities are completed, may provide skilled nursing facility level care to:</p>
                <p>(i) Honorably discharged veterans of the armed forces of the United States; and</p>
                <p>(ii) Members of the state national guard disabled while on duty.</p>
                <p>(b) Persons qualifying under subsection (a) of this section shall also be persons who:</p>
                <p>(i) By reason of wounds, disease, old age or other infirmities are unable to earn their living and have no adequate means of support; and</p>
                <p>(ii) Have been domiciled in this state for at least five (5) years next preceding their application for admission to the home.</p>
                <p>(c) The department of health may admit dependents of soldiers, sailors or disabled members of the national guard, if it deems admission proper.</p>
                <p>(d) There is created an account for use by the veterans' home of Wyoming for the general benefit of residents of the veterans' home. Profits from the sale of commodities at the veterans' home canteen after provision for increased inventories and servicing of the canteen facility and the interest earned from those profits shall be transferred to the account created by this subsection and are continuously appropriated to the department of health to be expended solely for the benefit of the veterans' home.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="69ed7ac2-1b42-4a55-9093-ee2e3527352a" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 9/25-9-102.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-9-102. When nonveterans permitted admission; preference to veterans and veterans' dependents.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The department of health may admit persons who are not veterans or dependents of veterans for care and treatment at the veterans' home of Wyoming if:</p>
                <p>(i) The home is not filled to ninety percent (90%) of capacity and there are pending no applications of veterans or veterans' dependents;</p>
                <p>(ii) The applicants are unable to earn their living and have no adequate means of support because of disease, old age or other infirmities;</p>
                <p>(iii) The applicants have been domiciled in this state for at least five (5) years next preceding their application for admission to the home;</p>
                <p>(iv) The persons are admitted pursuant to rules and regulations promulgated in accordance with W.S. 9-2-106(d).</p>
                <p>(b) In all cases veterans and dependents of veterans shall be given preference of admission.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="6008e953-899d-49cb-9445-8a297b3bee30" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 9/25-9-103.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-9-103. Acceptance of donations.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>The department of health on behalf of the state may accept donations of lands, money or other property.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="6a39ba3d-daf9-4281-97f7-57eae0ce9ce3" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 9/25-9-104.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-9-104. Medical care of residents; burial of deceased residents.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The department of health shall:</p>
                <p>(i) Furnish medical care for all residents of the home;</p>
                <p>(ii) Provide a place of burial; and</p>
                <p>(iii) Bury deceased residents.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="b75bebd5-7f91-41f6-bedf-6afa8fe4f7ed" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 9/25-9-105.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-9-105. Disposition of monies received from national home for disabled volunteer soldiers.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>Money received from the board of managers of the national home for disabled volunteer soldiers shall be deposited in a separate account. The money shall be expended by the department of health for the veterans' home of Wyoming.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="fbd9f49f-73fb-40e5-b952-22d1c5e712da" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 9/25-9-106.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-9-106. Chaplain; appointment; term; duties.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>The department of health may appoint a chaplain of the veterans' home of Wyoming who shall hold his office for a period of one (1) year from date of his appointment unless removed for cause. He shall have charge of the moral and intellectual welfare of the residents of the home. He shall visit the home at least twice a month and provide services therein as he desires.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
        <hcontainer GUID="9dbc2e64-df30-4266-bade-7a748867afc5" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 10 HOSPITALIZATION OF MENTALLY ILL PERSONS</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="df3df113-06c5-43c2-86e2-420ac34ec92f" name="4" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>ARTICLE 1 GENERAL PROVISIONS</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
            <hcontainer GUID="6d8dd3dc-3923-44f4-b22e-d9534b86e21f" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-101.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-101. Definitions.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) As used in this act:</p>
                  <p>(i) "Court" means the district court which ordered detention, directed outpatient commitment or involuntary hospitalization of the person pursuant to this act, or the district court in the county where the person resides, is found or is hospitalized;</p>
                  <p>(ii) "Dangerous to himself or others" means that, as a result of mental illness, a person:</p>
                  <p>(A) Evidences a substantial probability of physical harm to himself as manifested by evidence of recent threats of or attempts at suicide or serious bodily harm; or</p>
                  <p>(B) Evidences a substantial probability of physical harm to other individuals as manifested by a recent overt homicidal act, attempt or threat or other violent act, attempt or threat which places others in reasonable fear of serious physical harm to them; or</p>
                  <p>(C) Evidences behavior manifested by recent acts or omissions that, due to mental illness, he is unable to satisfy basic needs for nourishment, essential medical care, shelter or safety so that a substantial probability exists that death, serious physical injury, serious physical debilitation, serious mental debilitation, destabilization from lack of or refusal to take prescribed psychotropic medications for a diagnosed condition or serious physical disease will imminently ensue, unless the individual receives prompt and adequate treatment for this mental illness. No person, however, shall be deemed to be unable to satisfy his need for nourishment, essential medical care, shelter or safety if he is able to satisfy those needs with the supervision and assistance of others who are willing and available;</p>
                  <p>(D) While this definition requires evidence of recent acts or omissions of endangerment, either to self or others, a court may consider a person's mental health history in determining whether directed outpatient commitment or involuntary hospitalization is warranted.</p>
                  <p>(iii) "Department" means the state department of health;</p>
                  <p>(iv) "Examiner" means a licensed psychiatrist, a licensed physician, a licensed advanced practice registered nurse, a licensed physician assistant, a licensed psychologist, a licensed professional counselor, a licensed addictions therapist, a licensed clinical social worker or a licensed marriage and family therapist;</p>
                  <p>(v) "Head of hospital" means the individual in charge of a hospital or his designee. When this act requires or authorizes the head of a hospital to perform an act which involves the practice of medicine, the act shall be performed by a physician;</p>
                  <p>(vi) "Hospital" means a facility designated pursuant to W.S. 25-10-104 or the state hospital;</p>
                  <p>(vii) "Mental health center" means a community human services program for the prevention, treatment and amelioration of mental illness under W.S. 35-1-611 through 35-1-627 or an equivalently staffed and equipped student health service;</p>
                  <p>(viii) Repealed By Laws 1999, ch. 172, \xA7 3.</p>
                  <p>(ix) "Mental illness" and "mentally ill" mean a physical, emotional, mental or behavioral disorder which causes a person to be dangerous to himself or others and which requires treatment, but do not include addiction to drugs or alcohol, drug or alcohol intoxication or developmental disabilities, except when one (1) or more of those conditions co-occurs as a secondary diagnosis with a mental illness;</p>
                  <p>(x) "Patient" means an individual receiving treatment pursuant to this act;</p>
                  <p>(xi) "Physician" means an individual licensed under the laws of this state to practice medicine, or a physician in the service of the United States government while in this state in the performance of his official duties;</p>
                  <p>(xii) "State hospital" means the Wyoming state hospital at Evanston, Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(xiii) "Treatment" means diagnosis, evaluation, intervention, which may include psychiatric medication, individual and group mental health counseling, illness management diversion services such as immediate linkages to mental health services in the community and discharge planning. Treatment shall begin at the time of detention, if the person knowingly and voluntarily consents, and shall continue throughout involuntary hospitalization or directed outpatient commitment. Treatment may be given without the consent of the detained person or his parent or guardian when treatment is limited to diagnosis or evaluation or when treatment is necessary to prevent immediate and serious physical harm to the person or others. "Treatment" does not include observation or supervision;</p>
                  <p>(xiv) "Treatment center" or "treatment provider" means as defined by department rule;</p>
                  <p>(xv) "Resident" means a United States citizen who has been a resident of and domiciled in Wyoming for not less than ninety (90) days and who has not claimed residency elsewhere for the purpose of obtaining medical or psychiatric services during that ninety (90) day period immediately preceding the date when services under this act were sought or imposed. "Resident" also includes any alien who has resided continuously in Wyoming for at least ninety (90) days immediately prior to the date when services under this act were sought or imposed. "Resident" also includes any active duty member, the spouse or minor child of any active duty member of the armed forces of the United States who is stationed in Wyoming;</p>
                  <p>(xvi) "Gatekeeper" means the single point of responsibility which may be designated by the department pursuant to W.S. 25-10-112(g);</p>
                  <p>(xvii) "This act" means W.S. 25-10-101 through 25-10-305.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="f1e67eb8-7b3c-475d-b2d8-a33796cb6cb4" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-102.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-102. Admittees subject to rules and regulations of state hospital.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>All persons admitted to the state hospital shall be subject to the rules and regulations of the state hospital.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="2879cb0c-959e-4fc3-8006-780b8c35c823" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-103.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-103. Admission of persons with mental illness to hospital or treatment center.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>Subject to the rules and regulations of the department, a hospital or any other treatment provider providing treatment under this act may admit persons who have symptoms of mental illness for treatment in their hospital or treatment center.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="63aaf58f-33bc-4d28-9243-255cf9b2bfda" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-104.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-104. Duties of department of health as to hospitals other than state hospital.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) The department, with respect to hospitals or other treatment providers other than the state hospital, shall:</p>
                  <p>(i) Adopt standards for the designation of hospitals or other licensed treatment providers as qualified to accept patients and provide treatment under this act;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Designate hospitals or other treatment providers which qualify to provide services under this act;</p>
                  <p>(iii) Enter into contracts or agreements with designated hospitals or other treatment providers for the treatment of patients with mental illness;</p>
                  <p>(iv) Require information from designated hospitals and other treatment providers concerning the services rendered to patients under the provisions of this act;</p>
                  <p>(v) Repealed by Laws 2016, ch. 102, \xA7 3.</p>
                  <p>(vi) Investigate complaints made by or on behalf of patients with mental illness; and</p>
                  <p>(vii) Promulgate rules and regulations for the administration of this act, including rules regarding reimbursement under W.S. 25-10-112.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="de212ec4-91f5-4151-93bb-89649389711b" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-105.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-105. Duties of department of health as to state hospital.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) The department shall:</p>
                  <p>(i) Adopt standards governing the state hospital;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Visit the state hospital to review methods of treatment of patients; and</p>
                  <p>(iii) Investigate complaints made by or on behalf of state hospital patients.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="010c01e8-c726-4a67-84b0-78e1223658ab" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-106.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-106. Voluntary applications for admission.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) The head of a hospital may admit for treatment any adult who has symptoms of mental illness but who has sufficient insight or capacity to make responsible, voluntary application for admission and who applies for admission.</p>
                  <p>(b) A person who has symptoms of mental illness but because of minority or incompetency is not capable of making a responsible, voluntary application for admission may be admitted for treatment upon application by a parent or guardian if the application:</p>
                  <p>(i) Is accompanied by a statement of an examiner that the person is mentally ill; and</p>
                  <p>(ii) An examiner at the hospital, based on a personal interview, determines that the person is mentally ill.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="d510e06f-4367-4587-af75-81dc91384863" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-107.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-107. When voluntary patients shall be discharged.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>The head of a hospital shall discharge any patient admitted pursuant to W.S. 25-10-106(a) or (b) who no longer needs hospital treatment.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="d2595e4d-cdc7-483d-9ef6-aa83fd72f230" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-108.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-108. Release upon request; exceptions; discharge plan.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) A patient admitted pursuant to W.S. 25-10-106 who requests his release in writing or whose release is requested in writing by the person responsible for his care or custody, shall be released within twenty-four (24) hours after receipt of the request except:</p>
                  <p>(i) If the patient was admitted on his own application and the request for release is made by a person other than the patient, release may be conditioned upon the consent of the patient; or</p>
                  <p>(ii) If the patient is a minor or incompetent, his release may be conditioned upon the consent of his parent or guardian.</p>
                  <p>(b) The hospital shall prepare a discharge plan in accordance with policies, rules and regulations of the department.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="727dd52f-736b-4afa-8b82-4bc8df5c8299" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-109.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-109. Emergency detention.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) A person may be detained when:</p>
                  <p>(i) A law enforcement officer or examiner has reasonable cause to believe a person is mentally ill pursuant to W.S. 25-10-101;</p>
                  <p>(ii) A court has entered an ex parte order for immediate detention of a person pursuant to W.S. 25-10-110.1(h);</p>
                  <p>(iii) A hospital revokes convalescent status release of a person pursuant to W.S. 25-10-127(b) based on a previous or current determination of mental illness.</p>
                  <p>(b) Immediately after detaining the person, the officer shall contact an examiner. A preliminary examination of the person shall be conducted by an examiner within twenty-four (24) hours after the detention. If a preliminary examination is not conducted within twenty-four (24) hours the detained person shall be released. If the person is detained following the preliminary examination, an examiner shall reexamine the person not less than every forty-eight (48) hours until the hearing under subsections (h) through (k) of this section. If the examiner giving the preliminary examination, or any reexamination as required by this subsection, finds that the person:</p>
                  <p>(i) Is not mentally ill, the person shall be released immediately;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Was mentally ill, but is no longer dangerous to himself or others, the examiner shall, with patient consent, arrange follow up mental health care and the person shall be released immediately; or</p>
                  <p>(iii) Is mentally ill, the person may be detained for seventy-two (72) hours excluding Saturdays, Sundays and legal holidays.</p>
                  <p>(c) No person shall be detained for more than seventy-two (72) hours, excluding Saturdays, Sundays and legal holidays, without a hearing under subsections (h) through (k) of this section.</p>
                  <p>(d) A person taken into custody under this section may be detained in a hospital or other care setting which is appropriate under the circumstances and which complies with subsection (n) of this section. The person shall not be detained in a nonmedical facility used for detention of persons charged with or convicted of penal offenses except in extreme emergency or if there are no other reasonable alternatives. The law enforcement officer or examiner who detained the person shall immediately notify the person responsible for the care and custody of the detained person, if known, of the time and place of detention.</p>
                  <p>(e) The law enforcement officer or examiner who initially detained the person shall make a written statement of the facts of the emergency detention. A copy of the statement shall be given to the detained person, his parent or guardian, to any attorney representing the person, to the county attorney in the county where the person is detained, to any gatekeeper designated by the department and to any subsequent examiner.</p>
                  <p>(f) When a person is detained under emergency circumstances, treatment may be given during the emergency detention period if the person voluntarily and knowingly consents. The parent or guardian of a minor or incompetent person may consent to treatment. If the parent or guardian of a minor patient does not consent to treatment, a petition may be filed under the Child Protection Act. Treatment may be given without the consent of the detained person or his parent or guardian when treatment is limited to diagnosis or evaluation or when treatment is necessary to prevent immediate and serious physical harm to the person or others. Prior to treatment, the person shall be fully advised of the scope of treatment, and a report of the treatment shall be provided to the county attorney, to any gatekeeper designated by the department and shall be filed with the court if continued detention is sought, or if directed outpatient commitment or involuntary hospitalization proceedings are commenced. An examiner or a physician who provides treatment in good faith pursuant to this subsection shall be immune from civil liability for the treatment except there shall be no immunity from liability for negligent acts or deliberate misconduct.</p>
                  <p>(g) At the time of emergency detention the person shall be informed orally and in writing of his right to contact his family and an attorney, of his right to appointed counsel if he is indigent, of his right to remain silent and that his statements may be used as a basis for continued detention, directed outpatient commitment or involuntary hospitalization.</p>
                  <p>(h) When a person is detained in emergency detention and continued detention is sought, or an application for directed outpatient commitment or involuntary hospitalization is filed by the county attorney, the court shall appoint an attorney to represent the detained person unless he has his own attorney. The court shall conduct a hearing within seventy-two (72) hours, excluding Saturdays, Sundays and legal holidays, of the initial detention to determine whether continued detention is required pending directed outpatient commitment or involuntary hospitalization proceedings. The county attorney of the county where the application is filed shall appear on behalf of the state at the hearing. Any gatekeeper designated by the department pursuant to W.S. 25-10-112(g) shall appear at the hearing and provide testimony concerning continued detention and, if applicable, the issues outlined in subsection (m) of this section. Notice of the preliminary hearing shall be given to the county attorney, any gatekeeper designated by the department, the detained person and his parent, guardian and attorney. The court may delay the hearing only at the request of the detained person or his parent, guardian or his attorney.</p>
                  <p>The hearing for continued detention may be waived at the request of the detained person or the detained person's parent, guardian or attorney. If a hearing for continued detention has been waived, the court may immediately conduct the directed outpatient commitment or involuntary hospitalization hearing.</p>
                  <p>(j) At the hearing the court shall advise the detained person and his parent, guardian or attorney of the contents of the written statement of emergency detention required in subsection (e) of this section and the application for directed outpatient commitment or involuntary hospitalization.</p>
                  <p>(k) The standard of proof in an emergency detention hearing shall be by a preponderance of the evidence. If the court finds at an emergency detention hearing that:</p>
                  <p>(i) The person is not mentally ill, the court shall order the person released;</p>
                  <p>(ii) The person is mentally ill and has applied for and received voluntary admission, the court may dismiss the proceedings; or</p>
                  <p>(iii) The person is mentally ill, it shall order continued detention of the person for not more than ten (10) days. The court may extend the detention period at the request of the proposed patient or his attorney.</p>
                  <p>(m) If the court finds the person is mentally ill pursuant to paragraph (k)(iii) of this section, the court shall make findings as to the person's competence to make informed choices regarding treatment and the person's need for prescribed psychotropic medication. If the court finds the person incompetent to make an informed decision, the court may order the administration of prescribed psychotropic medication for the period of the emergency detention for restabilization of the person's mental health.</p>
                  <p>(n) Treatment provided as a result of an emergency or continued detention pursuant to this section shall be provided in the least restrictive and most therapeutic setting available with consideration given to requests of the detained person, his parent, guardian or attorney, and recommendations of any gatekeeper. Treatment may include the treatment options outlined in W.S. 25-10-110.1(d).</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="2706f08a-9919-4f25-af17-86a53d1f0c71" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-110.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-110. Involuntary hospitalization proceedings.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) Proceedings for the involuntary hospitalization of a person may be commenced by the filing of a written application with the court in the county in which the person is initially detained. Proceedings may also be initiated in the county in which there is a designated hospital if there is a written agreement executed by the county in which the person resides and the designated hospital stating that the county in which the person resides will be responsible for costs of treatment under W.S. 25-10-112(e) that are not covered by the state. The application shall be accompanied by either:</p>
                  <p>(i) A certificate of an examiner stating:</p>
                  <p>(A) That he has examined the proposed patient not more than fifteen (15) days prior to the date that the application was filed under this subsection;</p>
                  <p>(B) His findings and the proposed patient's history; and</p>
                  <p>(C) His opinion that the proposed patient is mentally ill; or</p>
                  <p>(ii) A written statement by the applicant and by an examiner that the proposed patient has refused to submit to examination by an examiner, together with a statement of the facts and circumstances supporting the application.</p>
                  <p>(b) Unless the proposed patient is represented by counsel, the court shall appoint an attorney to represent him.</p>
                  <p>(c) Proceedings under this section shall be entitled "In the Interest of ....". The county attorney of the county where the application is filed shall appear in the public interest. The court shall expedite the proceedings.</p>
                  <p>(d) Upon receipt of an application, the court shall issue notice thereof to the proposed patient, the person responsible for the care or custody of the proposed patient, any gatekeeper designated by the department and other persons designated by the court. The notice shall be served as provided by the Wyoming Rules of Civil Procedure. The notice shall apprise the proposed patient:</p>
                  <p>(i) Of the purpose of the proceeding;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Of the identity of the appointed examiner, and his authority to conduct an examination;</p>
                  <p>(iii) Of his right to counsel, the identity of counsel appointed by the court to represent him and his right to counsel of his own selection;</p>
                  <p>(iv) Of the requirements for an involuntary hospitalization order under subsection (j) of this section;</p>
                  <p>(v) Of the basis for the proposed hospitalization, including a detailed statement of the facts and supporting testimony;</p>
                  <p>(vi) That a hearing will be held if warranted by the report of the examination of the proposed patient; and</p>
                  <p>(vii) Of the identity of any gatekeeper designated by the department pursuant to W.S. 25-10-112(g).</p>
                  <p>(e) The court shall appoint one (1) or more examiners to examine the proposed patient and to make a written report to the court of the findings as to the history and mental illness of the proposed patient. The court may order the proposed patient to appear for examination and if the proposed patient does not appear the court may compel his appearance. The examination shall be held at a hospital, a medical facility, the home of the proposed patient or any other suitable place which will not have a harmful effect on his health. The examination shall be conducted no later than seven (7) days from the date of the notice. If the examination is conducted by an examiner other than a licensed physician, licensed psychiatrist or licensed psychologist, the court shall appoint a licensed physician, licensed psychiatrist or licensed psychologist to review the findings of the examiner and conduct a further examination, if indicated, and to report to the court.</p>
                  <p>(f) If the examiner reports the proposed patient is not mentally ill, the court shall terminate the proceedings. If the examiner reports the proposed patient is mentally ill, the court shall fix a date for and give notice of a hearing to be held as soon as possible. The notice shall satisfy the requirements of paragraphs (d)(i) through (vii) of this section.</p>
                  <p>(g) Within five (5) days of receipt of the notice of hearing, the proposed patient or his counsel may request a hearing before a jury. If upon the basis of the appointed examiner's report or from other information available to the court, the court concludes that the proposed patient does not understand his rights, the court may call a jury upon its own motion or upon the request of the person responsible for the care and custody of the proposed patient. A jury shall be selected pursuant to W.S. 1-11-101 through 1-11-129, and the proceedings shall follow the Wyoming Rules of Civil Procedure.</p>
                  <p>(h) The proposed patient, the applicant, and all others to whom notice is required may appear at the hearing to testify and may present witnesses. The court shall consider the testimony of any gatekeeper designated by the department and may receive the testimony of other persons. The proposed patient shall be present at the hearing unless he waives his right to appear. All persons not necessary to protect the rights of the parties shall be excluded from the hearing. The hearing shall be conducted in as informal a manner as is consistent with orderly procedure and in a physical setting which will not have a harmful effect on the mental health of the proposed patient. Any hearing conducted under this subsection shall be recorded by the court reporter or by electronic, mechanical or other appropriate means.</p>
                  <p>(j) If, upon completion of the hearing and consideration of the record, the court or the jury finds by clear and convincing evidence that the proposed patient is mentally ill the court shall consider the least restrictive and most therapeutic alternatives, give consideration to any recommendations by the gatekeeper and shall:</p>
                  <p>(i) Order his hospitalization, assign him to a hospital, and:</p>
                  <p>(A) Send to the hospital, with the patient a certified copy of the findings of fact and order and a copy of the examiner's report;</p>
                  <p>(B) Specify where he will be detained pending transportation to the hospital. No person shall be detained in a nonmedical facility used for detention of persons charged with or convicted of penal offenses except during an extreme emergency;</p>
                  <p>(C) Order his transportation to the hospital with proper clothing and personal effects;</p>
                  <p>(D) Notify his next of kin or the person responsible for his care and custody and the proposed treatment provider or hospital of the court's order;</p>
                  <p>(E) Make findings as to his competence to make informed choices regarding treatment and his need for prescribed psychotropic medication. If the court finds the person incompetent to make an informed decision, the court may order the administration of prescribed psychotropic medication. The order for medication shall be reviewed by a physician upon commitment and by a psychiatrist upon admission to the hospital. The prescribed medication shall be continued if found medically appropriate by the investigation review committee of the hospital or institution, subject to review by the medical director of the hospital or institution. Any action by the medical director of the hospital or institution shall be reviewable pursuant to the Wyoming Administrative Procedure Act. All orders for prescribed medication or a summary of all orders shall be provided to the gatekeeper designated by the department under W.S. 25-10-112(g).</p>
                  <p>(ii) Repealed by Laws 2016, ch. 102, \xA7 3.</p>
                  <p>(iii) Order the proposed patient be treated in a directed outpatient commitment pursuant to W.S. 25 10 110.1 if the court finds continuous inpatient hospitalization is not required and the proposed patient would be more appropriately treated in a directed outpatient commitment; or</p>
                  <p>(iv) Order any disposition for which private resources are available and which is consistent with the best interests of the proposed patient and with public safety.</p>
                  <p>(k) The court is authorized to appoint a special commissioner to assist in the conduct of hospitalization proceedings. In proceedings under this act, regularly appointed court commissioners may exercise the authority granted by W.S. 5-3-307. In any case in which the court refers an application to the commissioner, the commissioner shall conduct the directed outpatient commitment under W.S. 25-10-110.1 or the involuntary hospitalization proceedings under this section and on the basis thereof shall either recommend dismissal of the application or hold a hearing as provided in this section and make recommendations to the court regarding the disposition of the proposed patient and of the proceedings.</p>
                  <p>(m) An appointed examiner shall receive for his services in each court ordered examination a reasonable fee fixed by the court.</p>
                  <p>(n) The court shall inquire into the medical condition of every patient found to be mentally ill. If the court determines based upon the advice of a physician or other qualified professional, and in consultation with any gatekeeper designated by the department pursuant to W.S. 25-10-112(g), that the patient's present primary need is for medical treatment or care and whose need for psychiatric care is secondary, the court may delay ordering directed outpatient commitment or involuntary hospitalization of the patient until such time as the patient receives medical care and the patient's need for psychiatric care is primary.</p>
                  <p>(o) In proceedings under this section involving a minor, the court shall, to the extent feasible, consult with the minor's parents or legal guardian.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="24ae6084-e8f6-4d3f-a111-f96687091b28" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-110.1.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-110.1. Directed outpatient commitment proceedings.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) If the court finds based upon the recommendation of an examiner or on its own determination that the proposed patient is mentally ill but does not require inpatient hospitalization, the court shall consider issuing a directed outpatient commitment order. The court shall require directed outpatient commitment for the proposed patient for a period of time as determined appropriate by the court, not to exceed two (2) years with review by the court at least every six (6) months. The court may designate an outpatient care provider that will provide care to the proposed patient.</p>
                  <p>(b) In considering whether directed outpatient commitment is appropriate, the court may consider one (1) or more of the following:</p>
                  <p>(i) The proposed patient is diagnosed as having a mental illness;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Without directed outpatient treatment, the proposed patient is likely to be dangerous to himself or others based upon noncompliance with prior medical directives;</p>
                  <p>(iii) The proposed patient is likely to suffer substantial medical or mental deterioration or become seriously disabled;</p>
                  <p>(iv) The proposed patient lacks present ability to make an informed decision concerning his need for treatment; or</p>
                  <p>(v) Any other information concerning the proposed patient's need for outpatient care.</p>
                  <p>(c) The terms and conditions of the treatment plan shall be established by an examiner in consultation with any gatekeeper designated by the department and approved by the court. In preparing the plan, the examiner shall consult with the county attorney, treating health care providers and the patient or the person responsible for the care and custody of the patient, if known.</p>
                  <p>(d) The treatment plan may require:</p>
                  <p>(i) Periodic reporting;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Continuation of medication and submission to testing;</p>
                  <p>(iii) Restrictions on travel;</p>
                  <p>(iv) Restrictions on consumption of alcoholic beverages and drugs with requirements for any necessary testing;</p>
                  <p>(v) Use of community based group homes, crisis assistance centers or other available community based support services;</p>
                  <p>(vi) Temporary inpatient or residential treatment for stabilization;</p>
                  <p>(vii) Other conditions as agreed upon by the respective parties or as otherwise directed by the court.</p>
                  <p>(e) Treatment shall be provided by a treatment center or a court approved treatment provider.</p>
                  <p>(f) The treatment center or treatment provider or any other person identified in the treatment plan shall report to the county attorney and any gatekeeper designated by the department any material noncompliance by the patient with the treatment plan.</p>
                  <p>(g) By motion of an interested party or on its own motion, the court may revoke or modify the directed outpatient commitment if, after a hearing, the court finds by a preponderance of evidence that the patient violated any condition of the directed outpatient commitment order. If there has been a violation of the order, the court may modify the conditions of directed outpatient commitment, schedule an involuntary commitment hearing pursuant to W.S. 25-10-110, order any disposition for which private resources are available or order any disposition which is consistent with the best interests of the proposed patient and public safety.</p>
                  <p>(h) If a motion has been filed to modify or revoke the directed outpatient commitment, the court may enter an ex parte order for immediate detention of the patient if the court finds that the patient is a danger to himself or others. If the court enters an ex parte order of detention, the matter shall be set for hearing within seventy-two (72) hours. Notice of a hearing on a motion to modify or revoke the order for directed outpatient commitment shall be as provided in W.S. 25-10-110(d).</p>
                  <p>(j) The county attorney of the county where the directed outpatient commitment order is filed shall appear on behalf of the state at any hearing pursuant to this section.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="ee785340-8237-44e0-a598-bcdc21d4bb35" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-111.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-111. Commitment or transfer to federal hospital; effect of orders by courts of other jurisdictions; powers of federal facility.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) The court, when ordering involuntary hospitalization pursuant to W.S. 25-10-110(j), may order a person hospitalized in a hospital or facility operated by the veterans' administration or another federal agency, if the court has received a certificate from the agency showing that facilities are available and that the patient is eligible for treatment therein.</p>
                  <p>(b) An order of a court of competent jurisdiction of another state or of the District of Columbia, authorizing hospitalization of a person by an agency of the United States, has the same force and effect as to the person while in this state as in the jurisdiction in which the order was made.</p>
                  <p>(c) Upon receipt of a certificate from the veterans' administration or another federal agency that facilities are available for treatment of a patient involuntarily hospitalized under W.S. 25-10-110 and that the patient is eligible for treatment therein, the head of a hospital may transfer the patient to the veterans' administration or other federal agency for treatment. The court which ordered involuntary hospitalization shall be notified of the transfer by the hospital. No person shall be transferred if he is confined pursuant to a conviction for a crime or if he has been acquitted of a criminal charge solely on the ground of mental illness or deficiency, unless, prior to the transfer, the court which committed the person enters an order for the transfer after appropriate motion and hearing.</p>
                  <p>(d) Upon admission to a federal facility pursuant to this section, the patient is subject to the rules and regulations of the veterans' administration or other federal agency. The chief officer of the federal facility in which the patient is hospitalized has the same powers as the head of the state hospital with respect to retention, transfer, release and discharge of patients.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="6dc96a16-2c6d-47ad-8b62-77bcaa3754bf" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-112.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-112. Liability for costs of detention, involuntary hospitalization and proceedings therefor.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) Subject to the provisions of subsections (d) and (e) of this section, the county in which a person is detained or in which involuntary hospitalization proceedings are brought shall pay the costs of:</p>
                  <p>(i) The first seventy-two (72) hours of detention, in addition to any Saturday, Sunday or legal holiday that falls within the seventy-two (72) hours, pursuant to W.S. 25-10-109, including costs of medical treatment for those conditions:</p>
                  <p>(A) That resulted in the emergency detention of the person; or</p>
                  <p>(B) That are attributable to affirmative actions taken by the person that have placed the person in danger of suicide or serious bodily harm and require immediate medical attention.</p>
                  <p>(ii) Proceedings for detention or involuntary hospitalization pursuant to W.S. 25-10-109 or 25-10-110. The costs of these proceedings include the cost of appointed counsel and examiners;</p>
                  <p>(iii) Clothing, if the person does not have and cannot afford to purchase adequate clothing; and</p>
                  <p>(iv) Costs incurred under W.S. 25-10-125(b).</p>
                  <p>(b) Subject to the provisions of subsection (d) of this section, when a detained person or proposed patient is not a resident of Wyoming, the department shall pay the costs listed in paragraphs (a)(i) through (iii) of this section.</p>
                  <p>(c) The county shall pay for the first seventy-two (72) hours as provided in subsection (a) of this section even if the patient waives the hearing required under W.S. 25-10-109 and proceeds to voluntary outpatient treatment, directed outpatient commitment or involuntary hospitalization proceedings. Subject to the provisions of subsections (d) and (e) of this section, if continued emergency detention is ordered pursuant to W.S. 25-10-109(k)(iii), the county's liability for any costs of detention, treatment or transportation shall terminate after the first seventy-two (72) hours of detention, in addition to any Saturday, Sunday or legal holiday. The department shall be responsible for those costs after the expiration of the county's responsibility for payments of the costs. All costs of treatment, transportation and continued emergency detention incurred after the first seventy-two (72) hours of detention, in addition to any Saturday, Sunday or legal holiday, shall be paid by:</p>
                  <p>(i) The department for persons hospitalized in the state hospital; and</p>
                  <p>(ii) The department for persons hospitalized in other hospitals, consistent with W.S. 25-10-110(j) and 25-10-104.</p>
                  <p>(d) The hospital or other treatment provider shall attempt to recover all costs of treatment from public and private health insurance and from government benefit programs, including the veterans' administration, the Indian health service of the United States department of health and human services and any other federal agency that may be responsible for the costs of treatment, prior to seeking payment from the county or the department. The hospital or other treatment provider shall have discharged its obligation to recover costs under this subsection if it:</p>
                  <p>(i) Repealed by Laws 2016, ch. 102, \xA7 3.</p>
                  <p>(ii) Certifies to the county or the department that:</p>
                  <p>(A) The patient has no public or private health insurance;</p>
                  <p>(B) There are no other government benefit programs from which it can recover the costs of treatment; and</p>
                  <p>(C) If the patient might qualify for benefits, payment has been denied after submitting a written demand for payment to all federal agencies that may be responsible for the costs of treatment, including the veterans' administration and the Indian health service of the United States department of health and human services. Payment shall be deemed denied if a written demand for payment is made and no response is received within three (3) months of being properly submitted. If a demand is paid after having been deemed denied under this subparagraph, and after the county or department has paid the hospital or other treatment provider, the amount of the demand payment shall be remitted to the county or department, whichever entity paid the hospital or other treatment provider. If a county or the department has paid a hospital or other treatment provider, the county or the department shall have a subrogation right against any entity to whom the hospital or provider sent a written demand.</p>
                  <p>(e) When a person is detained under W.S. 25-10-109, the county in which the person resided shall be liable for costs of treatment for the first seventy-two (72) hours of detention, in addition to any Saturday, Sunday or legal holiday that falls within the seventy-two (72) hours. If the person remains in detention after the hearing pursuant to W.S. 25-10-109(k)(iii), the department shall directly, or under contract with local providers, provide treatment for those conditions specified in paragraph (a)(i) of this section until the person is released from detention or involuntary commitment is ordered, subject to payment of costs as provided in this subsection or subsection</p>
                  <p>(c) of this section.</p>
                  <p>(f) For purposes of this section, "costs" shall not include the expenses for any medical procedures that are not:</p>
                  <p>(i) Related to the assessment of or necessary treatment for the suspected mental illness; or</p>
                  <p>(ii) Otherwise specified in paragraph (a)(i) of this section.</p>
                  <p>(g) The department in consultation with each board of county commissioners may establish a single point of responsibility or gatekeeper. Gatekeeper duties shall include, but are not limited to, providing guidance on issues of detention and involuntary treatment and monitoring and coordinating timely, efficient and effective patient treatment prior to, during and after any emergency detention or involuntary treatment under this act. No gatekeeper designated under this subsection shall provide inpatient psychiatric treatment to patients under this act, unless the gatekeeper has been approved by the department of health to provide these services.</p>
                  <p>(h) The county attorney shall notify the department and any gatekeeper of any detention, continued emergency detention order, directed outpatient commitment or involuntary hospitalization order within twenty-four (24) hours.</p>
                  <p>(j) The department, boards of county commissioners, designated hospitals, gatekeepers and other treatment providers may, upon contract or agreement, coordinate and monitor the services and payments required for the treatment of persons with mental illness as provided under this section. Pursuant to contract or agreement, the department may assume any part of the expenses associated with a gatekeeper which expenses would otherwise be the responsibility of a county under this act, including expenses for the transportation of patients to appropriate care settings.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="43f10ee4-15c5-4232-88b0-3b55da9f93ad" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-113.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-113. Duties of head of hospital upon admission; treatment of patients primarily needing medical care.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) As soon as possible but not later than seven (7) days after a patient is admitted to a hospital under this act, the head of the hospital shall:</p>
                  <p>(i) Review the patient's record;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Examine the patient; and</p>
                  <p>(iii) Develop an initial plan of treatment for the patient.</p>
                  <p>(b) If the medical staff of the state hospital determines that a patient's primary need for care is medical as opposed to psychiatric, the head of the state hospital may refuse to admit the patient if the state hospital has limited medical facilities or staff to provide for the necessary medical needs of the patient. If admittance is refused, the patient shall be transported to a medical facility that is qualified to meet the medical needs of the patient.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="2e15529e-7c51-4b36-840a-532910caebf5" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-114.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-114. Transfer of inmates of penal institutions to state hospital; notice.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) The department of corrections may transfer an inmate of a state penal institution who is mentally ill to the state hospital, subject to the rules of admission of the state hospital, if adequate treatment cannot be provided at a state penal institution.</p>
                  <p>(b) Not less than five (5) days before an inmate is transferred pursuant to this section, the department of corrections shall give written notice to the court which ordered imprisonment, the inmate and the person responsible for his care or custody. The notice shall include:</p>
                  <p>(i) The grounds for the transfer;</p>
                  <p>(ii) The inmate's right to contest the transfer;</p>
                  <p>(iii) The inmate's right to a hearing before he is transferred; and</p>
                  <p>(iv) The inmate's right to counsel.</p>
                  <p>(c) The transfer of an inmate of a state penal institution to the state hospital shall not exceed the term of imprisonment imposed by the sentencing court unless proceedings for involuntary hospitalization are instituted under W.S. 25-10-110.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="9c8c39cd-7dc4-4f81-837e-4e21812ebacc" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-115.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-115. Transfer of patients to another hospital; notice.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) A hospital may transfer a patient hospitalized under this act to another hospital if the transfer is in the best interest of the patient. An involuntarily hospitalized patient who is so transferred retains the status of an involuntarily hospitalized patient under W.S. 25-10-110.</p>
                  <p>(b) Not less than five (5) days before a patient is transferred, the head of the hospital shall give written notice to the court, the patient, and the person responsible for his care or custody. The notice shall include:</p>
                  <p>(i) The grounds for the transfer;</p>
                  <p>(ii) The patient's right to contest the transfer;</p>
                  <p>(iii) The patient's right to a hearing before he is transferred; and</p>
                  <p>(iv) The patient's right to counsel.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="2e2055b7-139c-4080-a591-4d07f75b5735" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-116.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-116. Periodic examinations of patients; determination of discharge or continued hospitalization; notice; hearing.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) Three (3) months after each patient's admission to the hospital, the head of the hospital shall evaluate the progress of each patient and shall reevaluate the treatment and progress every six (6) months thereafter. The evaluation shall consider whether directed outpatient commitment is appropriate.</p>
                  <p>(b) When the head of a hospital determines after the examination required by subsection (a) of this section or by W.S. 25-10-113 that the conditions justifying hospitalization of involuntary patients no longer exist, he shall report his determination to the court, the county attorney, the district attorney, family members and the mental health center which were involved in the initial proceedings. Unless, within three (3) days after the notice is sent, the court upon motion orders a hearing on continuing the patient's hospitalization, the head of the hospital shall discharge the patient. The hearing shall be held as soon as practicable and shall follow the procedures in W.S. 25-10-118. Notice of the hearing shall conform with W.S. 25-10-116(c).</p>
                  <p>(c) When the head of a hospital determines after an evaluation required by subsection (a) of this section or by W.S. 25-10-113 that the conditions justifying hospitalization continue to exist, he shall send to the court notice of his determination and a detailed statement of the factual basis for the determination. The court may order a hearing to review the determination. The head of the hospital shall also send notice of his determination to the patient and the person responsible for his care or custody. The notice shall include:</p>
                  <p>(i) The patient's right to contest the determination;</p>
                  <p>(ii) The patient's right to a hearing; and</p>
                  <p>(iii) The patient's right to counsel.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="4553e5ef-7c7a-43ef-b468-0b6ec53edccc" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-117.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-117. Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 147, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="f8f34e0e-749f-485e-9a57-2ffc958f5886" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-118.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-118. Objections to proposed transfer or continued hospitalization; notice; hearing; options of court.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) A hearing shall be conducted in accordance with this section when a patient contests one (1) of the following actions:</p>
                  <p>(i) Transfer pursuant to W.S. 25-10-114 or 25-10-115;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Continuing hospitalization pursuant to W.S. 25-10-116; or</p>
                  <p>(iii) Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 147, \xA7 2.</p>
                  <p>(iv) Revocation of convalescent status release pursuant to W.S. 25-10-127.</p>
                  <p>(b) Unless otherwise provided, an objection shall be filed with the court within five (5) days of receipt of notice of the intended action. The court shall set a hearing date which shall be within fourteen (14) days of receipt of the objection. If an objection is not filed within five (5) days, or if the patient consents to the action, the court may enter an ex parte order authorizing the action.</p>
                  <p>(c) The hearing shall be before the court, without a jury. If the court finds by clear and convincing evidence that:</p>
                  <p>(i) The transfer or continuing hospitalization is justified, the court shall enter an order authorizing the transfer or continuing hospitalization; or</p>
                  <p>(ii) The transfer or continuing hospitalization is not justified, the court shall enter an order prohibiting the transfer or continuing hospitalization.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="d4cb0656-6348-453d-9c82-fa574216bac3" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-119.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-119. Mechanical restraints; uses and reasons therefor recorded.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>Mechanical restraints shall not be applied to any patient, unless the head of the hospital determines that the medical needs of the patient require them. The head of the hospital shall record every use of a mechanical restraint and the reasons for its use in the clinical record of the patient and sign the record.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="fd121b51-c7c4-48c0-8c98-ba768491d13f" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-120.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-120. Rights of patients; commitment and treatment of persons being treated by prayer.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) The department shall adopt rules and regulations creating a bill of patient rights and establishing the procedures by which those rights may be enforced, limited or denied.</p>
                  <p>(b) Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 147, \xA7 2.</p>
                  <p>(c) Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 147, \xA7 2.</p>
                  <p>(d) No person who is being treated in good faith by spiritual means alone, through prayer, by a duly accredited practitioner in accordance with the tenets and practices of a recognized church or religious denomination may be detained, hospitalized or ordered to receive treatment under this act unless:</p>
                  <p>(i) A court finds by clear and convincing evidence that he is mentally ill; or</p>
                  <p>(ii) If the person is a minor or is incompetent his parent or guardian consents to detention, hospitalization or treatment.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="85015f4c-b803-4608-9f06-d8e2b0bd91f7" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-121.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-121. Admission not to create presumption as to competency nor ground for guardianship.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>Admission to a hospital under this act shall not create any presumption with respect to the patient's mental or legal competency to exercise civil, contractual or other rights for which a legal standard of competency exists. Admission to a hospital under this act is not sufficient cause for guardianship of the person or estate of any patient.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="dbaf47ae-b21f-42f8-8679-30cf0df61cbc" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-122.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-122. Records to be kept confidential; exceptions.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) Records and reports made under this act which directly or indirectly identify a patient, a former patient or an individual for whom an application for directed outpatient commitment or involuntary hospitalization has been filed, shall be confidential and shall not be disclosed by any person unless:</p>
                  <p>(i) The patient or, if he is a minor or incompetent, his parent or guardian, consents;</p>
                  <p>(ii) Disclosure is necessary to carry out this act;</p>
                  <p>or</p>
                  <p>(iii) A court determines disclosure is necessary for the conduct of proceedings before it and failure to disclose would be contrary to the public interest.</p>
                  <p>(iv) Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 147, \xA7 2.</p>
                  <p>(b) Patient records identified in subsection (a) of this section may be provided without consent of the patient, parent or guardian by and between a mental health center, the state hospital and hospitals designated under W.S. 25-10-104, only for the purpose of facilitating referral treatment, admission, readmission or transfer of the patient under this act.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="3e31e367-be61-4287-8bf9-12d159ed5b68" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-123.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-123. Discharge of patient held on order in action arising out of criminal offense.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>A patient held on order of a court having criminal jurisdiction in any action or proceeding arising out of a criminal offense shall not be discharged except upon order of a court of competent jurisdiction. At any time the head of the hospital is of the opinion that the person is no longer affected by mental illness or deficiency, or that he no longer presents a substantial risk of danger to himself or others, the head of the hospital shall apply to the court which committed the person for an order of discharge. The court having criminal jurisdiction in the matter shall conduct a hearing not less than once each year to determine whether the continued hospitalization of the patient is necessary, based on the reports required under W.S. 25-10-116 and any other information provided to the court by the state hospital or the federal hospital under W.S. 25-10-111, as appropriate, or the patient's counsel. After a hearing, the court shall make its findings and enter an order as provided in W.S. 25-10-118(c).</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="d60952a3-3452-42eb-a360-d46ca4f83fb1" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-124.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-124. Transfer of patients between states.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 147, \xA7 2.</p>
                  <p>(b) Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 147, \xA7 2.</p>
                  <p>(c) Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 147, \xA7 2.</p>
                  <p>(d) Transfer of patients between states shall be governed by the Interstate Compact on Mental Health, W.S. 25-10-301.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="8e7b6579-688e-4058-87c2-07c8673e94a3" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-125.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-125. Clothing and transportation upon discharge.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) The department, pursuant to W.S. 25-10-112 shall ensure that a patient discharged from the state's custody possesses suitable clothing and adequate means to ensure his arrival at the home from which he was admitted or another place within the state, which is in the best interests of the state and of the patient.</p>
                  <p>(b) The county responsible for payment of costs pursuant to W.S. 25-10-112(a) shall ensure that a patient discharged from emergency detention within seventy-two (72) hours, or upon expiration of emergency detention after seventy-two (72) hours without a court order for hospitalization under W.S. 25-10-110, possesses suitable clothing and adequate means to ensure his arrival at the home from which he was admitted or another place, which is in the best interests of the county and of the patient.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="5241d61f-8a59-48c9-978b-9d489c66c7b7" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-126.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-126. Penalties for unwarranted hospitalization or denial of rights.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) A person who willfully causes the unwarranted hospitalization of any individual under this act is guilty of a felony punishable by a fine not exceeding five thousand dollars ($5,000.00) or imprisonment not exceeding five (5) years, or both.</p>
                  <p>(b) A person who willfully denies any individual any of the rights accorded to him under this act is guilty of a misdemeanor punishable by a fine not exceeding seven hundred fifty dollars ($750.00) or imprisonment not exceeding six (6) months, or both.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="d23a8649-a080-46a0-864b-c5183f55fd9c" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-127.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-127. Convalescent status; discharge; readmittance.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>(a) After providing notice to the court, the county attorney who initiated involuntary hospitalization procedures, any gatekeeper designated by the department and all interested parties, the hospital may release an improved patient on convalescent leave subject to the following:</p>
                  <p>(i) The hospital has determined that the patient is likely to follow the conditions the hospital determines necessary for the patient;</p>
                  <p>(ii) The hospital has determined that the patient will not likely be a danger to himself or others during convalescent leave; and</p>
                  <p>(iii) Release on convalescent leave shall include a plan of treatment on an outpatient or nonhospital basis and other provisions for continuing responsibility of the patient by the hospital. Prior to the end of one (1) year on convalescent leave, and not less than annually thereafter, the hospital shall reexamine the facts relating to the hospitalization of the patient on convalescent leave and if the hospital determines hospitalization is no longer anticipated, the hospital shall discharge the patient and make a report of discharge to the court, to any gatekeeper designated by the department and to the county attorney who initiated procedures for the involuntary hospitalization.</p>
                  <p>(b) The hospital from which the patient is given convalescent leave may readmit to the hospital the involuntary hospitalized patient who has been released on convalescent leave if the hospital reasonably believes that it is in the best interests of the patient. The patient readmitted shall have all the rights he had upon admission to the hospital. Upon readmission he shall be given notice of his rights pursuant to W.S. 25-10-116. It is the responsibility of the hospital to provide or pay for any transportation or other services in connection with any revocation of a convalescent status.</p>
                  <p>(c) The hospital shall discharge any patient who has remained on convalescent leave for a period of two (2) continuous years.</p>
                  <p>(d) This section shall not apply to a person who has been committed to the hospital pursuant to a criminal proceeding.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="ac2ca264-f6a6-430a-9100-fad52ed451fc" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-128.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-128. Access to patient information.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>Any disclosure of patient information required by this article shall be subject to limitations imposed by state and federal law. The department shall promulgate rules facilitating the exchange of information required by this article to the maximum extent allowed by state and federal law. At the discretion of the court considering a matter under this article, the court may order the disclosure of information required by this article.</p>
                  <p>The court also may designate and direct the actions of a gatekeeper otherwise designated by the department under W.S. 25-10-112(g) for the purpose of allowing the gatekeeper access to patient information.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="0e7bf9af-f6ba-4d26-af72-b817cf949021" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 1/25-10-129.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-129. Receipt and disposition of revenues and gifts.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>The department is authorized to deposit all monies and income received and collected by the Wyoming state hospital into a special revenue account. The department shall expend this revenue to correct life safety code problems, pay for the cost of emergency detentions pursuant to W.S. 25-10-109, pay for the costs of involuntary hospitalizations pursuant to W.S. 25-10-110, and remediate conditions at the state hospital as identified in settlement agreements which are approved by the director and reported to the governor. If any single capital project is anticipated to exceed two hundred thousand dollars ($200,000.00), it shall be approved by the state building commission. The department shall report to the joint appropriations committee not later than November 1 of each year detailing expenditures under this section.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="51c5a207-5cdd-4726-b055-2f8298c259f0" name="4" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>ARTICLE 2 FISCAL PROVISIONS</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
            <hcontainer GUID="94e22f9d-b14f-46c8-86e4-61ce5a395543" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-201.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-201. Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="f5483254-1f28-41ce-b4e1-3ef90882b016" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-202.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-202. Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="dc81ef90-c842-4d2c-820f-e7f5c36ccbc0" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-203.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-203. Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="e5699bd2-f81d-4ec6-bc5b-f8fcf68c0bcf" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-204.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-204. Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="ef274920-237e-4242-af1c-b6956ab11d5e" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-205.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-205. Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="1328ed34-6f4e-4553-8fbf-c6f93ae9eeed" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-206.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-206. Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="e980dbfb-cf4e-4c88-a734-93d54783f1f0" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-207.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-207. Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="fb79abab-72be-41e0-8d52-07f2ef72f0a2" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-208.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-208. Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="f121d71d-17dd-4e11-9166-19fc067b62ba" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-209.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-209. Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="c2d373bc-907b-4689-a492-c106c10ebbac" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-210.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-210. Repealed by Laws 1985, ch. 221, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="b88c2d2e-e3ef-47dc-ae07-95918bbaf197" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-211.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-211. Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="a2bda271-e92b-406f-acd0-6e3a3cecc79a" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-212.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-212. Repealed by Laws 1987, ch. 27, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="10ca8b36-361f-4243-b3a9-e821ae2cf8e5" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-213.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-213. Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="e0e7f819-2d96-4359-91dd-10903fbca15a" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 2/25-10-214.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-214. Repealed by Laws 1989, ch. 50, \xA7 4.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="8a618c01-90b9-4fb0-8dd7-1d566d3fca60" name="4" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 3">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>ARTICLE 3 INTERSTATE COMPACT ON MENTAL HEALTH</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
            <hcontainer GUID="6efd13fd-cd63-45f2-8c45-2989b404d80a" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 3/25-10-301.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-301. Enactment into law; form.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>The Interstate Compact on Mental Health is hereby enacted into law and entered into by this state with all other states legally joining therein in the form substantially as follows:</p>
                  <p>Article I</p>
                  <p>The party states find that the proper and expeditious treatment of the mentally ill and mentally deficient can be facilitated by cooperative action, to the benefit of the patients, their families, and society as a whole. Further, the party states find that the necessity of and desirability for furnishing such care and treatment bears no primary relation to the residence or citizenship of the patient but that, on the contrary, the controlling factors of community safety and humanitarianism require that facilities and services be made available for all who are in need of them. Consequently, it is the purpose of this compact and of the party states to provide the necessary legal basis for the institutionalization or other appropriate care and treatment of the mentally ill and mentally deficient under a system that recognizes the paramount importance of patient welfare and to establish the responsibilities of the party states in terms of such welfare.</p>
                  <p>Article II</p>
                  <p>(a) As used in this compact:</p>
                  <p>(i) "Sending state" shall mean a party state from which a patient is transported pursuant to the provisions of the compact or from which it is contemplated that a patient may be so sent;</p>
                  <p>(ii) "Receiving state" shall mean a party state to which a patient is transported pursuant to the provisions of the compact or to which it is contemplated that a patient may be so sent;</p>
                  <p>(iii) "Institution" shall mean any hospital or other facility maintained by a party state or political subdivision thereof for the care and treatment of mental illness or mental deficiency;</p>
                  <p>(iv) "Patient" shall mean any person subject to or eligible as determined by the laws of the sending state, for institutionalization or other care, treatment, or supervision pursuant to the provisions of this compact;</p>
                  <p>(v) "Aftercare" shall mean care, treatment and services provided a patient, as defined herein, on convalescent status or conditional release;</p>
                  <p>(vi) "Mental illness" shall mean mental disease to such extent that a person so afflicted requires care and treatment for his own welfare, or the welfare of others, or of the community;</p>
                  <p>(vii) "Mental deficiency" shall mean mental deficiency as defined by appropriate clinical authorities to such extent that a person so afflicted is incapable of managing himself and his affairs, but shall not include mental illness as defined herein;</p>
                  <p>(viii) "State" shall mean any state, territory or possession of the United States, the District of Columbia, and the commonwealth of Puerto Rico.</p>
                  <p>Article III</p>
                  <p>(a) Whenever a person physically present in any party state shall be in need of institutionalization by reason of mental illness or mental deficiency, he shall be eligible for care and treatment in an institution in that state irrespective of his residence, settlement or citizenship qualifications.</p>
                  <p>(b) The provisions of paragraph (a) of this article to the contrary notwithstanding, any patient may be transferred to an institution in another state whenever there are factors based upon clinical determinations indicating that the care and treatment of the patient would be facilitated or improved. Any institutionalization may be for the entire period of care and treatment or for any portion or portions thereof. The factors referred to in this paragraph shall include the patient's full record with due regard for the location of the patient's family, character of the illness and probable duration and other factors as shall be considered appropriate.</p>
                  <p>(c) No state shall be obliged to receive any patient pursuant to the provisions of paragraph (b) of this article unless the sending state has given advance notice of its intention to send the patient; furnished all available medical and other pertinent records concerning the patient; given the qualified medical or other appropriate clinical authorities of the receiving state an opportunity to examine the patient if said authorities so wish; and unless the receiving state shall agree to accept the patient.</p>
                  <p>(d) In the event that the laws of the receiving state establish a system of priorities for the admission of patients, an interstate patient under this compact shall receive the same priority as a local patient and shall be taken in the same order and at the same time that he would be taken if he were a local patient.</p>
                  <p>(e) Pursuant to this compact, the determination as to the suitable place of institutionalization for a patient may be reviewed at any time and further transfer of the patient may be made as seems likely to be in the best interest of the patient.</p>
                  <p>Article IV</p>
                  <p>(a) Whenever, pursuant to the laws of the state in which a patient is physically present, it shall be determined that the patient should receive aftercare or supervision, such care or supervision may be provided in a receiving state. If the medical or other appropriate clinical authorities having responsibility for the care and treatment of the patient in the sending state shall have reason to believe that aftercare in another state would be in the best interest of the patient and would not jeopardize the public safety, they shall request the appropriate authorities in the receiving state to investigate the desirability of affording the patient aftercare in the receiving state, and an investigation shall be made with all reasonable speed. The request for investigation shall be accompanied by complete information concerning the patient's intended place of residence and the identity of the person in whose charge it is proposed to place the patient, the complete medical history of the patient, and any other documents as may be pertinent.</p>
                  <p>(b) If the medical or other appropriate clinical authorities having responsibility for the care and treatment of the patient in the sending state and the appropriate authorities in the receiving state find that the best interest of the patient would be served and if the public safety would not be jeopardized the patient may receive aftercare or supervision in the receiving state.</p>
                  <p>(c) In supervising, treating, or caring for a patient on aftercare pursuant to the terms of this article, a receiving state shall employ the same standards of visitation, examination, care, and treatment that it employs for similar local patients.</p>
                  <p>Article V</p>
                  <p>Whenever a dangerous or potentially dangerous patient escapes from an institution in any party state, that state shall promptly notify all appropriate authorities within and without the jurisdiction of the escape in a manner reasonably calculated to facilitate the speedy apprehension of the escapee.</p>
                  <p>Immediately upon the apprehension and identification of any dangerous or potentially dangerous patient, he shall be detained, in the state where found pending disposition in accordance with law.</p>
                  <p>Article VI</p>
                  <p>The duly accredited officers of any state party to this compact, upon the establishment of their authority and the identity of the patient, shall be permitted to transport any patient being moved pursuant to this compact through any and all states party to this compact, without interference.</p>
                  <p>Article VII</p>
                  <p>(a) No person shall be deemed a patient of more than one (1) institution at any given time. Completion of transfer of any patient to an institution in a receiving state shall have the effect of making the person a patient of the institution in the receiving state.</p>
                  <p>(b) The sending state shall pay all costs of and incidental to the transportation of any patient pursuant to this compact, but any two (2) or more party states may, by making a specific agreement for that purpose, arrange for a different allocation of costs as among themselves.</p>
                  <p>(c) No provision of this compact shall be construed to alter or affect any internal relationships among the departments, agencies and officers of and in the government of a party state, or between a party state and its subdivisions, as to the payment of costs, or responsibilities.</p>
                  <p>(d) Nothing in this compact shall be construed to prevent any party state or subdivision from asserting any right against any person, agency or other entity in regard to costs for which the party state or subdivision may be responsible pursuant to any provision of this compact.</p>
                  <p>(e) Nothing in this compact shall be construed to invalidate any reciprocal agreement between a party state and a nonparty state relating to institutionalization, care or treatment of the mentally ill or mentally deficient, or any statutory authority pursuant to which the agreements may be made.</p>
                  <p>Article VIII</p>
                  <p>(a) Nothing in this compact shall be construed to abridge, diminish, or in any way impair the rights, duties, and responsibilities of any patient's guardian on his own behalf or in respect of any patient for whom he may serve, except that where the transfer of any patient to another jurisdiction makes advisable the appointment of a supplemental or substitute guardian, any court of competent jurisdiction in the receiving state may make a supplemental or substitute appointment and the court which appointed the previous guardian shall upon being duly advised of the new appointment, and upon the satisfactory completion of the accounting and other acts as the court may by law require, relieve the previous guardian of power and responsibility to whatever extent shall be appropriate in the circumstances; provided, however, that in the case of any patient having settlement in the sending state, the court of competent jurisdiction in the sending state shall have the sole discretion to relieve a guardian appointed by it or continue his power and responsibility, whichever it shall deem advisable. The court in the receiving state may, in its discretion, confirm or reappoint the person or persons previously serving as guardian in the sending state in lieu of making a supplemental or substitute appointment.</p>
                  <p>(b) The term "guardian" as used in paragraph (a) of this article shall include any guardian, trustee, legal committee, conservator, or other person or agency however denominated who is charged by law with power to act for or responsibility for the person or property of a patient.</p>
                  <p>Article IX</p>
                  <p>(a) No provision of this compact except article V shall apply to any person institutionalized while under sentence in a penal or correctional institution or while subject to trial on a criminal charge, or whose institutionalization is due to the commission of an offense for which, in the absence of mental illness or mental deficiency, said person would be subject to incarceration in a penal or correctional institution.</p>
                  <p>(b) To every extent possible, it shall be the policy of the states party to this compact that no patient shall be placed or detained in any prison, jail or lockup, but the patient shall, with all expedition, be taken to a suitable institutional facility for mental illness or mental deficiency.</p>
                  <p>Article X</p>
                  <p>(a) Each party state shall appoint a "compact administrator" who, on behalf of his state, shall act as general coordinator of activities under the compact in his state and who shall receive copies of all reports, correspondence, and other documents relating to any patient processed under the compact by his state either in the capacity of sending or receiving state. The compact administrator or his duly designated representative shall be the official with whom other party states shall deal in any matter relating to the compact or any patient processed.</p>
                  <p>(b) The compact administrators of the respective party states shall have power to promulgate reasonable rules and regulations to carry out more effectively the terms and provisions of this compact.</p>
                  <p>Article XI</p>
                  <p>The duly constituted administrative authorities of any two (2) or more party states may enter into supplementary agreements for the provision of any service or facility or for the maintenance of any institution on a joint or cooperative basis whenever the states concerned shall find that agreements will improve services, facilities, or institutional care and treatment in the field of mental illness or mental deficiency. No supplementary agreement shall be construed so as to relieve any party state of any obligation which it otherwise would have under other provisions of this compact.</p>
                  <p>Article XII</p>
                  <p>This compact shall enter into full force and effect as to any state when enacted by it into law and the state shall be a party with any and all states legally joining.</p>
                  <p>Article XIII</p>
                  <p>(a) A state party to this compact may withdraw therefrom by enacting a statute repealing the same. Such withdrawal shall take effect one (1) year after notice thereof has been communicated officially and in writing to the governors and compact administrators of all other party states. However, the withdrawal of any state shall not change the status of any patient who has been sent to said state or sent out of said state pursuant to the provisions of the compact.</p>
                  <p>(b) Withdrawal from any agreement permitted by article VII(b) as to costs or from any supplementary agreement made pursuant to article XI shall be in accordance with the terms of the agreement.</p>
                  <p>Article XIV</p>
                  <p>This compact shall be liberally construed so as to effectuate the purposes. The provisions of this compact shall be severable and if any phrase, clause, sentence or provision of this compact is declared to be contrary to the constitution of any party state or of the United States or the applicability to any government, agency, person or circumstance is held invalid, the validity of the remainder of this compact and the applicability to any government, agency, person or circumstance shall not be affected. If this compact shall be held contrary to the constitution of any state party, the compact shall remain in full force and effect as to the remaining states and in full force and effect as to the state affected as to all severable matters.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="960bb60a-fc70-49a2-9056-eb4f72216346" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 3/25-10-302.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-302. Designation, powers and duties of compact administrator.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>Pursuant to the compact, the director of the department of health is authorized and empowered to designate an officer who shall be the compact administrator and who, acting jointly with like officers of other party states, shall have power to promulgate rules and regulations to carry out more effectively the terms of the compact. The compact administrator is authorized, empowered and directed to cooperate with all departments, agencies and officers of and in the government of this state and its subdivisions in facilitating the proper administration of the compact or any supplementary agreement or agreements entered into by this state.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="b5af9381-b371-4779-a209-565226c249e4" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 3/25-10-303.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-303. Supplementary agreements; approval required for full force and effect.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>The compact administrator is authorized and empowered to enter into supplementary agreements with appropriate officials of other states pursuant to articles VII and XI of the compact. In the event that the supplementary agreements shall require or contemplate the use of any institution or facility of this state or require or contemplate the provision of any service by this state, no agreement shall have force or effect until approved by the head of the department or agency under whose jurisdiction the institution or facility is operated or whose department or agency will be charged with the rendering of the service.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="d5a2895f-8d89-49b8-8a63-d569129443f5" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 3/25-10-304.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-304. Discharge of financial obligations with director's approval.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>The compact administrator, subject to the approval of the director, may make or arrange for any payments necessary to discharge any financial obligations imposed upon this state by the compact or by any supplementary agreement entered into thereunder.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="e12617be-f999-4a3e-a6dc-21bad96a37f6" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 3/25-10-305.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-305. Consultation with family of proposed transferee; court approval of final action.</shortTitle></p>
                  <p>The compact administrator is directed to consult with the immediate family of any proposed transferee and, in the case of a proposed transferee from an institution in this state to an institution in another party state, to take no final action without approval of an appropriate state district court.</p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="58e6e1bf-3325-48d8-98bb-0145915eefdc" name="4" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 4">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>ARTICLE 4 JUVENILE TREATMENT PROGRAM</shortTitle></p>
              </content>
            </level>
            <hcontainer GUID="b7f94bd5-f022-4424-85fa-10bb3054cd20" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 4/25-10-401.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-401. Repealed by Laws 1990, ch. 24, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="51fbd348-786f-470b-a60f-a891dd621513" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 4/25-10-402.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-402. Repealed by Laws 1990, ch. 24, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="e596ed98-dc95-45a4-b0f2-8b3ce5e9a3df" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 4/25-10-403.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-403. Repealed by Laws 1990, ch. 24, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
            <hcontainer GUID="2ace0bce-7350-4cdd-831b-32556930183a" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 10/ARTICLE 4/25-10-404.">
              <level>
                <content>
                  <p><shortTitle>25-10-404. Repealed by Laws 1990, ch. 24, \xA7 2.</shortTitle></p>
                </content>
              </level>
            </hcontainer>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
        <hcontainer GUID="1b0cb59e-e110-43ca-94b3-0f4b090e7e05" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 11">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 11 FISCAL PROVISIONS</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="9f1e9f0f-e0e8-460c-8592-299c287b5cc4" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 11/25-11-101.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-11-101. Definitions.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) As used in this chapter:</p>
                <p>(i) "Actual cost" means the cost of providing treatment or services for a resident in a state institution including minimum costs, as set by the department having the direct authority and control of the institution, of maintaining the resident;</p>
                <p>(ii) Repealed by Laws 1991, ch. 221, \xA7 3.</p>
                <p>(iii) "Established charge" means that part of the actual cost for which the resident, the resident's estate and legally responsible persons are liable. The established charge may equal but not exceed the actual cost;</p>
                <p>(iv) "Legally responsible person" means the resident, a responsible relative or the conservator of the resident's property as defined by W.S. 3-1-101(a)(iii);</p>
                <p>(v) "Resident" means a patient or resident voluntarily admitted or involuntarily committed to a state institution;</p>
                <p>(vi) "Responsible relative" means a resident's spouse or a resident's parents if the resident is an unemancipated minor;</p>
                <p>(vii) "State institution" means any institution in title 25 under the direct authority and control of the department of health.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="addd4223-0990-4d0f-93d1-a0de30b396b6" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 11/25-11-102.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-11-102. Department to adopt schedule of costs for services and treatments; residents' accounts.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The department of health shall promulgate on or before October 1 of each year a schedule of actual costs for services and treatment rendered residents at each state institution under the direct authority and control of the department.</p>
                <p>(b) In determining actual costs the department may subtract from operation costs capital outlay and real property repair and maintenance to determine the immediate benefit to the resident.</p>
                <p>(c) An account for each resident shall record the actual costs and established charge for each month or fraction thereof. The established charge shall be paid in the manner provided in this article and credited to the account of the resident.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="a6c46006-37a5-495d-b4a8-30ca8d29ae2d" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 11/25-11-103.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-11-103. Determining financial ability and established charges; special funds considered as part of resident's assets.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) Established charges shall be determined using a sliding scale promulgated by the department of health or the department of family services for each state institution under its direct authority and control. The sliding scale shall be based upon the ability of the resident or other legally responsible person to pay and shall be designed to provide that the resident or legally responsible person shall not be deprived of income necessary to maintain a reasonable standard of living for that person and his dependents.</p>
                <p>(b) Upon completion of a resident questionnaire form provided by the department, the director of the department shall determine the established charge to be assessed in each case using the sliding scale promulgated by the department. Any payor may protest his established charge through the head of the institution to the department exercising direct authority and control over the institution if still dissatisfied. The department may affirm the established charge or set a different established charge. The decision of the department may be appealed pursuant to the Wyoming Administrative Procedure Act.</p>
                <p>(c) Any available income and special funds, including but not limited to hospitalization insurance, social security benefits, disability compensation, pensions, retirement benefits and veterans' benefits shall be considered part of the total assets of a resident in determining an established charge.</p>
                <p>(d) Nothing in this chapter limits any obligation created by law or contract for third parties to pay for services provided to a resident admitted to a state institution.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="52fd9598-4c11-40fb-9f2d-c1308adad7a5" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 11/25-11-104.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-11-104. Reimbursement of general fund for payments.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>Payments for services provided to a resident admitted to a state institution either voluntarily or involuntarily shall be reimbursed to the state general fund.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="c1545045-50e4-4b4b-a02f-df7f33058961" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 11/25-11-105.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-11-105. Limitation on liability of responsible relatives; liability of relatives, patient and estate after release or death; exception.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The liability of a parent or spouse of a resident for payment of established charges shall not exceed two (2) years of cumulative care at the state institution. Voluntary payments for care in excess of the two (2) year limitation may be accepted. This section does not limit the obligation, created by contract or law, of third party payments for resident or temporary services.</p>
                <p>(b) Subject to the limitation in subsection (a) of this section, the resident, his estate and other legally responsible persons are liable after release of the resident for the payment of any unpaid established charge. If a resident or a released resident dies, his estate is liable for all unpaid established charges unless the department exercising direct authority and control over the institution determines that no claim or a lesser claim should be filed against the estate due to the need for support from the proceeds of the estate of the legal dependents of the resident who are the beneficiaries of his estate.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="246d32a3-5b29-486e-98af-77cfe6862f2f" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 11/25-11-106.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-11-106. Billings; assignment of insurance; collection or waiver of arrearages.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The department of health shall establish procedures requiring state institutions under its direct authority and control to provide monthly billings to each resident of the state institution and to each legally responsible person. Billings under this subsection for the state hospital shall provide for an itemization, including at a minimum, the daily established charge.</p>
                <p>(b) The department shall obtain an assignment of benefits from any resident under its care and supervision who has insurance that may cover services provided.</p>
                <p>(c) An account for established charges which is not paid within ninety (90) days after the end of the month in which the charges accrue is in arrears and shall be referred to the respective department for collection. The department may contract with a private person or agency for collection of accounts under this subsection.</p>
                <p>(d) The department may adjust, compromise or waive collection of charges from the legally responsible person if the department determines that the person is without financial means or that collection would constitute a hardship. If the department decides to waive collection of charges, no future billing will be sent to a resident or legally responsible person.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="042a551b-a7a1-4c9c-b8ae-c04db677e36b" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 11/25-11-107.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-11-107. State to bear costs of those unable to pay.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>If a resident or legally responsible person has no available assets at the time of or during the resident's stay at a state institution to pay an established charge, all costs of treatment and transportation shall be borne by the state.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="0968991b-b16f-4dc1-a8bc-9615e3784465" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 11/25-11-108.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-11-108. Department to promulgate rules; forms.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>The department of health shall promulgate reasonable rules and regulations and shall approve and provide forms necessary to carry out the purposes of this chapter.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
        <hcontainer GUID="8d5b8f21-1bcc-4590-8192-7a4c8aa099dc" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 12">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 12 WYOMING SCHOOL FOR THE DEAF</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="d6c18e08-6dc6-4730-ae35-ee0c58c5ab13" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 12/25-12-101.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-12-101. Wyoming school for the deaf; establishment; purpose; supervision.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The Wyoming school for the deaf is established at Casper, Wyoming, to provide to every child of school age in the state of Wyoming who is hearing impaired and for whom no lesser restrictive placement can be provided by the local school district a free and appropriate education in accordance with the child's capabilities.</p>
                <p>(b) The Wyoming school for the deaf shall be operated and maintained under the general supervision of the superintendent of public instruction pursuant to W.S. 21-2-202. The superintendent shall promulgate rules and regulations for the administration of the program and shall facilitate continued cooperation with Natrona county school district number 1. The school shall be staffed as follows:</p>
                <p>(i) Except for substitute teachers who shall hold a substitute teaching permit, teachers at the school shall hold a Wyoming standard teaching certificate, including an endorsement for deaf education;</p>
                <p>(ii) The administrator at the school shall hold a Wyoming standard teaching certificate, including endorsements for deaf education and school principal;</p>
                <p>(iii) Interpreters at the school shall be qualified under rules promulgated by the department of education;</p>
                <p>(iv) Ancillary staff shall be qualified for the positions they hold.</p>
                <p>(c) The program may serve as a repository for equipment and materials to assist local agencies serving individuals with hearing impairments.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
        <hcontainer GUID="b8f57169-1851-42ba-b00c-553adc7f4900" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 13">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 13 CORRECTIONAL INDUSTRIES PROGRAM</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="a38f0343-ee00-48cb-9971-9b5ea2099b5e" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 13/25-13-101.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-13-101. Definitions.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) As used in this act:</p>
                <p>(i) "Advisory board" or "board" means the correctional industries advisory board created by W.S. 25-13-102;</p>
                <p>(ii) "Department" means the department of corrections;</p>
                <p>(iii) "Inmate" means a person serving a felony sentence in a state correctional facility;</p>
                <p>(iv) "State correctional facility" means the Wyoming state penitentiary, the Wyoming women's center or any penitentiary honor farm or camp;</p>
                <p>(v) "This act" means W.S. 25-13-101 through 25-13-107.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="89db10a9-774c-4d46-9d6e-1d606944c952" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 13/25-13-102.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-13-102. Correctional industries advisory board.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) There is created the correctional industries advisory board. The board shall consist of seven (7) members appointed by the governor. Members shall serve a three (3) year term provided that of the initial board, two (2) members shall be appointed for a one (1) year term, two (2) members for two (2) year terms and three (3) members for three (3) year terms. Membership on the board shall include representatives of organized labor, business, the criminal justice system and the educational community. The director of the department of corrections and the director of the department of workforce services, or their designees, shall serve as ex officio nonvoting members of the board.</p>
                <p>(b) The governor may remove any member of the board as provided by W.S. 9-1-202.</p>
                <p>(c) Vacancies on the advisory board shall be filled by appointment for the unexpired term.</p>
                <p>(d) Members of the advisory board shall not receive compensation for their services, but when actually engaged in the performance of their duties shall receive travel expenses, per diem and mileage expenses in the same manner and amount as employees of the state.</p>
                <p>(e) The department shall provide staff services as the advisory board requires to carry out its duties.</p>
                <p>(f) The advisory board shall recommend to the governor and to the department policies for correctional industries programs designed to:</p>
                <p>(i) Offer inmates meaningful employment, work experience and training in vocations that are specifically designed to reduce recidivism and thereby enhance public safety by providing opportunities for legitimate means of livelihood upon the inmate's release from custody;</p>
                <p>(ii) Provide industries which will reduce the tax burden of corrections and save taxpayers money through production of goods and services for sale and use;</p>
                <p>(iii) Provide for the effective and efficient operation of correctional work programs which are as similar as possible to those provided by the private sector;</p>
                <p>(iv) Encourage the development of and provide for the selection of, contracting for, and supervision of work programs with participating private enterprise firms; and</p>
                <p>(v) Provide advice regarding the use of available funds in correctional industries enterprises and meaningful work programs that will not result in the displacement of employed workers, be applied in skills, crafts or trades in which there is adequate gainful labor in the locality or impair existing contracts for services.</p>
                <p>(g) The advisory board shall annually review and report to the governor and joint judiciary interim committee the performance of the correctional industries program within the department.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="100f2aff-4557-4cb0-8a82-ea5f1f960b11" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 13/25-13-103.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-13-103. Correctional industries account.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) There is created the correctional industries account. The department shall deposit in the account all monies collected under W.S. 25-13-107(b)(iii) and all other revenues or profits that accrue from the operation of the correctional industries program created by this act until the account balance reaches five million dollars ($5,000,000.00). Annually, on July 1, monies within the account in excess of five million dollars ($5,000,000.00) shall be credited to the general fund as reimbursement to the state for costs of incarceration. Interest on funds in the account shall remain in the account.</p>
                <p>(b) Monies in the account shall be appropriated only for expenses related to the establishment, operation and enhancement of the correctional industries program and vocational programs at state correctional facilities.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="c9882ff9-8f1c-4502-8ab3-9b5a8c2c6c88" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 13/25-13-104.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-13-104. Agreements with private employers; leases.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The department, in consultation with the correctional industries advisory board, may establish programs for the employment of inmates by private employers and enter into agreements with private employers under which the employer owns, constructs, leases to or from the department or otherwise establishes facilities to manufacture or process goods, provide services or conduct any other business, commercial or agricultural enterprise and employ inmates from a correctional facility. Facilities established under this section may be located within or outside the exterior boundaries of a state correctional facility property. Construction of facilities by private employers under this section shall not be subject to competitive bid requirements applicable to construction by the state. Inmate labor may be used pursuant to W.S. 7-16-202 for construction of facilities that occurs within the exterior boundaries of a state correctional facility property under this section.</p>
                <p>(b) If any state correctional facility operates a program involving the use, purchase, training or sale of wild horses, the program shall not use any wild horse which was not initially captured or found within the boundaries of the state or within the boundaries of a bureau of land management herd management area contiguous to the state. There shall be a brand and ownership inspection under W.S. 11-20-203 at the time of transfer of a wild horse to or from any state correctional facility. Not later than November 1 of each year, the department shall report to the joint agriculture, state and public lands and water resources interim committee on any use of or other transactions involving wild horses at correctional facilities in this state. As used in this section, "wild horse" means as defined in W.S. 11-30-115(a).</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="8f052035-1589-4317-a6c3-7fe2f37d1df9" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 13/25-13-105.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-13-105. Voluntary employment.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>An inmate may be employed under this act only on a voluntary basis and only after the inmate has been informed of all conditions of employment.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="2177f4b6-5e50-4458-b21f-0afacdb91a26" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 13/25-13-106.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-13-106. Application of other laws.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The employer shall contribute to the state worker's compensation fund at the appropriate rate calculated by the worker's compensation division for the work being performed.</p>
                <p>(b) A nongovernmental enterprise operating on any correctional facility premises under this act is subject to all laws and rules otherwise governing the operation of similar private enterprises in this state.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="447cd694-836d-4317-9979-cbf52b8a233f" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 13/25-13-107.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-13-107. Compensation of employed inmates; payment and disposition.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) Any agreement entered into between the department and a private employer under this act shall provide that an employed inmate shall be paid wages at a rate which is not less than that paid for work of a similar nature in the locality in which the work is performed.</p>
                <p>(b) The compensation of an inmate employed under this act shall be surrendered to the department and shall be distributed in the following order:</p>
                <p>(i) Fifteen percent (15%) of the inmate's gross compensation under the program to the inmate's personal savings account within the correctional facility's trust and agency account, until the inmate's account has a balance of up to two thousand five hundred dollars ($2,500.00). Once the inmate's personal savings account balance reaches two thousand five hundred dollars ($2,500.00), this fifteen percent (15%) shall be distributed to the inmate as provided by W.S. 7-16-205(a). Funds in the inmate's personal savings account shall be paid to the inmate upon parole or final discharge;</p>
                <p>(ii) Twenty percent (20%) of the inmate's gross compensation under the program to be distributed to the inmate as provided by W.S. 7-16-205(a);</p>
                <p>(iii) Deduction for federal income taxes, medicare and social security appropriate to the gross amount of the inmate's compensation under the program;</p>
                <p>(iv) Fifteen percent (15%) of the remaining amount to the crime victims compensation account created by W.S. 1-40-114;</p>
                <p>(v) If the inmate is not obligated to pay child support, the remaining amount to the correctional industries account pursuant to W.S. 25-13-103(a), to reduce the cost otherwise associated with providing the inmate with room and board;</p>
                <p>(vi) If the inmate is obligated for existing child support obligations, pursuant to state statute or court order, including all support obligations issued pursuant to W.S. 20-2-102, the remainder of the inmate's compensation under the program, shall be distributed toward the child support obligation up to the amount ordered. If the existing child support obligation is less than the remainder of the inmate's compensation under the program, the difference between the actual amount of the child support obligation and the remainder of the inmate's compensation under the program shall be distributed to the correctional industries account pursuant to W.S. 25-13-103(a), to reduce the cost otherwise associated with providing the inmate with room and board;</p>
                <p>(vii) The department shall provide all inmates employed under this act with the forms necessary for the filing of a petition for support under W.S. 20-2-102 and shall honor new or existing court orders for support up to the amount ordered, including those orders issued pursuant to a petition for support filed under W.S. 20-2-102.</p>
                <p>(c) The department shall develop the necessary administrative structure to recover inmates' wages and keep records of the amount inmates pay for the costs of incarceration.</p>
                <p>(d) The earnings of inmates under this act are not subject to garnishment, attachment or execution either in the hands of the employer, the department or any agent authorized to hold and transmit the earnings.</p>
                <p>(e) If a provision of this act relating to the payment or disbursement of compensation to inmates employed in a correctional industries program conflicts with any other provision of title 27 of the Wyoming Statutes, the provision of this act controls.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
        <hcontainer GUID="aab79ac0-eb8c-4798-9c6f-55e82ba0a8d9" name="3" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 14">
          <level>
            <content>
              <p><shortTitle>CHAPTER 14 WYOMING VETERANS' SKILLED NURSING FACILITY</shortTitle></p>
            </content>
          </level>
          <hcontainer GUID="36c23888-c2b8-4c1f-a846-15eed3287767" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 14/25-14-101.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-14-101. Purpose; admission of veterans and veterans' spouses; admission of "gold star" nonveterans; preference to veterans and veterans' spouses; capacity.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The Wyoming veterans' skilled nursing facility is created to provide veterans with skilled nursing benefits across multiple levels of need. The skilled nursing facility shall provide community living, care and treatment for individuals who, due to wounds, disease, old age or other infirmities as determined by department of health rules, need safety net care because they cannot be served in private facilities, skilled nursing care or subsidized long-term care benefits and who are:</p>
                <p>(i) Honorably discharged veterans of the armed forces of the United States; or</p>
                <p>(ii) Members of the state national guard disabled while on duty.</p>
                <p>(b) The department of health may admit to the Wyoming veterans' skilled nursing facility a spouse of a person who qualifies under subsection (a) of this section, pursuant to rules or orders the department promulgates in accordance with W.S. 9-2-106(d) or 25-14-105.</p>
                <p>(c) The department of health may admit persons to the Wyoming veterans' skilled nursing facility for care and treatment who are not qualifying veterans or spouses of veterans under subsection (a) or (b) of this section if:</p>
                <p>(i) The persons are qualifying dependents or the parents of United States military personnel who died while in service or who died as a result of their service as provided by statute, rule or regulation of the United States department of veterans affairs; and</p>
                <p>(ii) The persons are admitted pursuant to rules or orders promulgated in accordance with W.S. 9-2-106(d) or 25-14- 105.</p>
                <p>(d) Veterans and spouses of veterans who qualify for admission under subsections (a) and (b) of this section shall be given preference of admission in all circumstances.</p>
                <p>(e) In addition to subsections (a) through (d) of this section, the veterans' skilled nursing facility shall comply with United States department of veterans affairs rules regarding capacity guidelines, number of beds and populations served.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="e5234eca-8f87-419b-b115-3e8cfe0806f1" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 14/25-14-102.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-14-102. Veterans' skilled nursing facility account; disposition, receipt and expenditure of monies received; acceptance of funding and donations.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) There is created the veterans' skilled nursing facility special revenue account. Notwithstanding W.S. 9-4- 303(a), the department of health, veterans' commission and state construction department shall deposit all monies and income received and collected by or for the Wyoming veterans' skilled nursing facility into the account. Monies in this account are continuously appropriated to pay the costs of design and planning, construction, operation, loan repayment and maintenance of the veterans' skilled nursing facility.</p>
                <p>(b) The department of health on behalf of the state may accept:</p>
                <p>(i) State, federal, local and nongovernmental funds for the purposes of this chapter provided that any condition on receipt of the funds is not inconsistent with this chapter;</p>
                <p>(ii) Donations of land, money or other property for the construction, maintenance or other benefit of the veterans' skilled nursing facility.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="9e61f9da-4ec7-408d-a6b8-242a3405556c" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 14/25-14-103.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-14-103. Services for residents; administration; facility operation.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>(a) The department of health shall, by contract or otherwise:</p>
                <p>(i) Provide skilled nursing care in the veterans' skilled nursing facility in accordance with the federal Social Security Act and the federal Medicare and Medicaid regulations and United States department of veterans affairs requirements;</p>
                <p>(ii) Appoint one (1) department of health employee to oversee federal and state requirements applicable to the veterans' skilled nursing facility;</p>
                <p>(iii) Provide other care as required under authority of the director of the department of health pursuant to W.S. 9- 2-106(d).</p>
                <p>(b) The department of health may contract with an organization to provide day-to-day operation and administrative management of the veterans' skilled nursing facility. The contract may provide for a monthly management fee as the department of health determines. The contract for operations and administrative management shall be in accordance with the best practices of a "green house" model community living concept and shall comply with state and federal law and regulations.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="d68c905b-2414-450e-96c7-9a9e33f2c4b7" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 14/25-14-104.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-14-104. Payments for care.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>Residents shall pay for services provided under this chapter according to department of health rules. Payments shall be set at amounts to ensure that appropriate services are provided at the veterans' skilled nursing facility, as required by this chapter, and shall be consistent with requirements for grant in aid payments from the United States department of veterans affairs.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
          <hcontainer GUID="23bcff06-e42c-46b0-9d3b-b62ce8decc2f" name="5" class="/US/US-WY/WYOMING_STATUTES/TITLE 25/CHAPTER 14/25-14-105.">
            <level>
              <content>
                <p><shortTitle>25-14-105. Promulgation of rules.</shortTitle></p>
                <p>The department of health shall promulgate rules necessary to carry out this chapter. The rules shall provide admission requirements that do not jeopardize the veterans' skilled nursing facility's, or any veteran's, qualifications to receive federal financial aid during admission to the veterans' skilled nursing facility.</p>
              </content>
            </level>
          </hcontainer>
        </hcontainer>
      </hcontainer>
    </mainBody>
  </doc>
</akomaNtoso>

